<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Allegiance vindicated, or, The takers of the new oath of allegiance to K. William &amp; Q. Mary justified and the lawfulness of taking it asserted, in its consistency with our former oaths, and also with the doctrine of the Reformed Church of England, concerning non-resistance &amp; passive obedience / by a Divine of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>A. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23002</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12234832</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12234832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56717</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26679)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56717)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 47:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Allegiance vindicated, or, The takers of the new oath of allegiance to K. William &amp; Q. Mary justified and the lawfulness of taking it asserted, in its consistency with our former oaths, and also with the doctrine of the Reformed Church of England, concerning non-resistance &amp; passive obedience / by a Divine of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694.</term>
               <term>Allegiance --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56717:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56717:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ALLEGIANCE VINDICATED:</hi> OR, The TAKERS OF THE New OATH of ALLEGIANCE TO K. <hi>William</hi> &amp; Q. <hi>Mary</hi> JUSTIFIED: AND THE Lawfulneſs of taking it Aſſerted, in its Conſiſtency with our former Oaths; and alſo with the Doctrine of the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> CONCERNING NON-RESISTANCE &amp; PASSIVE OBEDIENCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Divine of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pidgeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56717:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56717:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Takers of the new Oath of Allegiance to King</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary <hi>vindicated: and the Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of taking it aſſerted, in its conſiſtency with our former Oaths; and alſo with the Doctrine of the</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church <hi>of</hi> England <hi>concerning</hi> Non-reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance <hi>and</hi> Paſſive Obedience.</head>
            <p>IT appears ſufficiently by this Time, (I ſuppoſe,) upon <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> that the generality of the Reverend, Learned, and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Clergy</hi> of this Church have actually taken the <hi>Oath</hi> in Diſpute: and their <hi>Books</hi> every where extant declare, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them have written Learnedly in Defence of themſelves and their Brethren ſo doing: and have not been wanting in their utmoſt endeavours to ſatisfie thoſe of them who yet refuſe, by offering them all the Arguments they could think of, for it; and turning every Stone under which they could imagine any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable objection againſt it to lie concealed, in order to the giving it a ſatisfactory Solution.</p>
            <p>They have, to this purpoſe, unravelled all the <hi>Principles of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and ſearched into the Reaſon of them all, even from <hi>Adam,</hi> downwards; they have, particularly, with great induſtry, ſifted the <hi>Legal Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Monarchy,</hi> and the Hiſtory of all its <hi>Monarchs,</hi> to evidence the <hi>Original Contract,</hi> upon which it is aſſerted, that our Government is founded; they have endeavoured to evince the <hi>late King</hi> to have been a kind of <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> (as to his Title thereunto,) by voluntary <hi>Abdicating</hi> the <hi>Throne;</hi> to which divers Authors alſo have added his Legal <hi>Forfeiture,</hi> (as they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,) by breaking the <hi>Original Contract</hi> before-mentioned: they have fortified the Claim and Title of our <hi>preſent Sovereigns,</hi> by juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the late <hi>Dutch Invaſion,</hi> together with the riſing of the Engliſh Nobility, and their adherents, in the circumſtances wherein we then
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56717:3"/> were, to aſſiſt it; they have pleaded the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Conqueſt</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent thereupon, if their <hi>Preſent Majeſties</hi> had thought fit to fix their Throne on that foundation; and (that being waved by them, who have rather choſen to adventure themſelves upon the <hi>favour</hi> of the Nation Aſſembled in <hi>Parliament,)</hi> they have aſſerted the <hi>Legality</hi> of the <hi>preſent Parliament,</hi> for <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> although wanting the uſual <hi>circumſtances</hi> of <hi>Summons,</hi> &amp;c. (which in the preſent conjuncture could not be had,) to conſtitute them in all points formally ſuch; and (by Conſequence) have inferred the <hi>validity</hi> of thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> for the <hi>ſettlement</hi> of the <hi>Throne,</hi> which they have made; and thereby, not only juſtified the <hi>matter</hi> of this <hi>Oath,</hi> but alſo, the <hi>Authority</hi> by which it is impoſed: and laſtly, they have (by ſtrong Evidence to that Point, at leaſt, if all other grounds ſhould fail,) made out the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> (if not <hi>neceſſary Duty)</hi> of paying our <hi>Actual Obedience</hi> to their <hi>Majeſties,</hi> as <hi>actually poſſeſſed</hi> of the <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet (notwithſtanding all theſe Endeavours of theirs,) it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears alſo, that divers of the <hi>Sacred Function</hi> (and ſome of them of the <hi>higheſt Character,</hi> and <hi>Station</hi> in this Church,) have, rather than to comply with the reſt in taking this <hi>Oath,</hi> already incurred the Penalty of <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> from, and ſeem inclined yet farther to hazard the being totally <hi>deprived</hi> (which is the Penalty to which Refuſers are ſhortly endangered) of their <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Employments:</hi> which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declares, that all that hath been ſaid upon that ſubject yet, hath not been prevalent enough for their plenary ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof, I muſt confeſs, may very well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage any Perſon who hath but modeſty enough to take a juſt meaſure of himſelf (in compariſon with thoſe who have Written before ſo accurately on this Argument, as to leave little for any that comes after them to add thereunto) from attempting any thing farther of that kind; and had certainly had that effect upon my ſelf, had I not found it neceſſary, in a ſort, (upon the account of the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable carriage</hi> of divers Perſons, who, though it may be, they have not ſo much as looked into any of the Books before-mentioned to underſtand the Reaſons moving us thereto, have made it much of their buſineſs to cenſure and condemn both my ſelf, and ſo many of my <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> as have taken the ſaid Oath,) to write a few Lines in <hi>Juſtification,</hi> (at leaſt) of that which <hi>we</hi> have done: if not, alſo, to the <hi>conviction</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> who ſtill ſtand out in their refuſal, and the inducing of them to do the ſame yet, before the approaching expiration of the <hi>Term</hi> by the <hi>Act</hi> allowed, and the ſecuring themſelves in thoſe <hi>Stations,</hi> wherein they may ſtill continue
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56717:3"/> ſerviceable to this Church; to which divers of them, (as all muſt acknowledge) have hitherto been, both a <hi>Defence</hi> by their learned <hi>Pens,</hi> and an <hi>ornament</hi> by their <hi>perſonal Qualifications.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſenſible (I muſts needs ſay) by Experience, that with the <hi>Aſſertors</hi> of ſome <hi>rigorous Principles of Loyalty,</hi> all the Arguments urged from the Topicks before-mentioned, except thoſe of the <hi>laſt</hi> ſort, are of no conſideration at all: and that even <hi>thoſe,</hi> (although they find from them ſome fairer Quarter then the reſt, <hi>in Theſi,</hi> or in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, yet) in the <hi>preſent Caſe,</hi> are judged inſufficient and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding. And this, becauſe they are ſtrongly poſſeſſed with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, that their <hi>former Allegiance</hi> is a thing of an everlaſting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Obligation, and in no ſort or degree, upon any emergency, to be transferred from a <hi>Prince</hi> however <hi>diſpoſſeſſed,</hi> (as one, who hath a <hi>Title,</hi> neither <hi>forfeitable</hi> by any <hi>miſcarriage,</hi> nor <hi>voidable</hi> by any <hi>ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> or <hi>departure)</hi> unto any <hi>other,</hi> ſo long as he lives, and is not pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed expreſly to releaſe it: and adhere to the Doctrines of <hi>Non-reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> (as they judge them taught by the Church of <hi>England)</hi> to ſuch a Degree, as to pronounce them utterly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the <hi>Allegiance</hi> in this <hi>Oath</hi> required. So that, when we have to do with Men of that ſtrain, it is neceſſary that we wave all thoſe <hi>former Heads</hi> of Arguments above-mentioned; and caſt the whole ſtreſs of this Diſpute upon the laſt, in the Iſſue of this ſingle <hi>Queſtion,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Whether, (with the ſaving of thoſe Principles of theirs, be they ſound or not) a Man that profeſſeth Loyalty in its utmoſt rigours, may not yet be at liberty, in the preſent circumſtances, to take the Oath required to K.</hi> W. <hi>and Q.</hi> M. <hi>as actual Poſſeſſors of the Throne?]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this, therefore, I reſolve in this Diſcourſe, to confine my ſelf; endeavouring to prove the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> and anſwer all viſible <hi>Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to the contrary, in the making good the <hi>Propoſitions</hi> following. The <hi>firſt</hi> whereof, is this,</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>[That in all Places, every one that is by Law in the condition of a Subject owes a Legal Obedience</hi> (which I take to be no other then Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance) <hi>to ſome ſupreme Powers; and to ſome Perſon or Perſons by whom it is exerciſed.] Subjection,</hi> from <hi>Subjects,</hi> is always <hi>due</hi> ſomewhere, <hi>under what Form of Government ſoever Men be, by the Law of Nature,</hi> (according to the Reverend Dr. <hi>Sanderſon:)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Caſe of the Engagement</note> and <hi>that, (primarily)</hi> to <hi>every Mans Country, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, to the Sovereign Power thereof.</hi> For the denial of this, does evidently involve a contradiction; as that which ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the <hi>ſame Perſon,</hi> at the ſame time, a <hi>Subject,</hi> and yet <hi>no Subject:</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56717:4"/> a <hi>Subject,</hi> as being under the <hi>Laws;</hi> and yet <hi>no Subject,</hi> as being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from that <hi>Duty</hi> which thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> enjoyn. Yea, more, it vertually diſſolves (while it is denied) that <hi>Society</hi> (in the tendency thereof) which is eſtabliſhed upon, and maintained by thoſe Laws. For the Obligation of the Law at any time diſſolved, leaves every Man (ſo long as things continue in that poſture) <hi>ſui juris,</hi> in the equality of Nature; ſo that he may challenge, without reſtraint, the liberty of <hi>doing what is good in his own Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II <hi>That this Legal Obedience, or Allegiance, cannot in the preſent juncture, be actually paid to</hi> King James, <hi>and therefore the Obligation of it ſo far ceaſeth, as to its actual performance to him, as he is in an actual incapacity to demand, or we to give it; how due ſoever (according to the Principles mentioned) it may be thought to be.</hi> This Notion here aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of the <hi>Ceſſation of actual Obedience,</hi> (though promiſed by an Oath) I take to be (as to its poſſibility) agreeable to the Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the learned Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> in his famous Book, <hi>De Obligatione Juramenti;</hi> who therein pronounceth a promiſſory Oath (as to its Obligation to Performance) to ceaſe, <hi>per ceſſationem materiae,</hi> when the matter of it ceaſeth. Now, the <hi>matter</hi> of an <hi>Oath Promiſſory</hi> then <hi>ceaſeth,</hi> when that which is promiſed, is not payable; which may happen, either by its becoming either naturally or morally <hi>impoſſible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for inſtance, when the <hi>Perſon</hi> to whom the <hi>Promiſe</hi> is made, ceaſeth to be in a capacity to demand or receive what was ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. This (I ſuppoſe) may fall out; either <hi>totally,</hi> as (in one of the Doctors own Inſtances) it does, when the <hi>General</hi> of an <hi>Army,</hi> to whom a Soldier is obliged by a <hi>Military Oath</hi> is dead. Then, it is <hi>caſſated,</hi> or made totally void. Or, <hi>partially,</hi> as (to keep to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer inſtance) when the <hi>General</hi> ſo ſworn to, though he be yet alive, is notwithſtanding in ſuch circumſtances as render him, for the time, <hi>as dead;</hi> which may happen, by his being <hi>taken Priſoner,</hi> and ſhut up ſo cloſe, as that the Soldier can receive no certain Commands from him. I could here alſo (if I may without offence) add <hi>another Caſe</hi> (which, whether it diſſolve ſuch an Obligation <hi>totally,</hi> or <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially</hi> only, let who will determine) to wit, When ſuch a <hi>General voluntarily deſerts his Army;</hi> and eſpecially if he do ſo, to <hi>joyn</hi> himſelf with their Enemies; ſo that he cannot in thoſe circumſtances be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Party he hath deſerted, without the Breach of an <hi>higher Obligation</hi> to him, or them, from, or for whom he received his Commiſſion. Now I am very much miſtaken if <hi>one</hi> of theſe Caſes run not parallel with <hi>ours,</hi> in the <hi>Allegiance</hi> promiſed to <hi>King James.</hi> For, plain it is, <hi>de facto,</hi> that we can, in his preſent cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56717:4"/> have no <hi>Communication</hi> with him, nor receive any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Commands</hi> from him, how willing ſoever we might be to ſerve him; being (whether by choice or neceſſity, I determin not here) wholly in the power of our <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Religions</hi> profeſſed Enemies; without maintaining that dangerous <hi>Intelligence</hi> which he himſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in reaſon require; and which, I hope, our moſt <hi>diſſatisfied Brethren</hi> do not think that <hi>Allegiance</hi> obligeth us at this <hi>time,</hi> to keep with him. And I could wiſh that the <hi>later</hi> Caſe propounded, did not alſo run <hi>too parallel</hi> with ours, <hi>i. e.</hi> That he had not embodied himſelf with the ſworn Adverſaries of our Religion (as to his Communion) as he hath long ſince; and yet, notwithſtanding that, we paid him our true Allegiance always whiles he ſtayed among us, which he himſelf hath more than once acknowledged. And much more, that he had not now at laſt alſo, not only <hi>deſerted</hi> us, but likewiſe armed againſt us thoſe of that Party who moſt thirſt after our Blood; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by rendred it farther impoſſible for any <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> (eſpecially <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants)</hi> to pay him that further Duty which the Oath of Allegiance expreſſeth by <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Defence;</hi> which they cannot do (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the preceding Hypotheſis) without breaking their greater <hi>antecedent Oligations</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> their <hi>Native Country, themſelves</hi> and their <hi>Poſterity;</hi> in conſiſtence wherewith, all ſubſequent Obligations muſt be interpreted, to render them lawful: For, otherwiſe, the Rule is <hi>Prior obligatio praejudicat poſteriori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To clear up this <hi>Propoſition</hi> the more fully; let us ſpend a little time in enquiring particularly into thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which may by any one be ſuppoſed to be due to <hi>King James</hi> in his preſent cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; and ſee, whether any of them be rationally performable to him, by the <hi>Engliſh Clergy</hi> particularly, to whoſe Caſe this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is chiefly aecommodated.</p>
            <p>The <hi>main Duty</hi> of our <hi>former Allegiance</hi> is contain'd in the Words of <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> and <hi>Defence,</hi> as was before ſaid. This is done, either by <hi>Arms;</hi> or <hi>otherwiſe;</hi> to wit, by actions more proper to our Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As to the <hi>former;</hi> I ſuppoſe no Man of that Calling will think himſelf obliged perſonally to bear Arms for him. For an entire freedom herein was always allowed us by the Law, which excuſeth all <hi>Perſons in Holy Orders</hi> from being required to do ſo in any caſe. So that whatever is at any time done, of that nature, by any of them, muſt needs be, in this caſe, not a matter of Duty, but a meer <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogation of Loyalty,</hi> a perfectly voluntary and free-will Offering. It would be no other, even to a <hi>Prince</hi> that had moſt highly <hi>deſerved</hi> of us; and one, whom (in the <hi>proſpect</hi> of the <hi>Succeſs</hi> of his Arms)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56717:5"/> we could <hi>cordially truſt</hi> with all our deareſt <hi>Intereſts.</hi> And therefore it is not to be ſuppoſed that any conſidering Perſon of that Order (how militarily diſpoſed ſoever he may be otherwiſe) will think fit perſonally to give one, who ſurely hath not ſo <hi>obliged</hi> us, and the <hi>Succeſs</hi> of whoſe Arms at preſent we cannot ſafely <hi>Truſt,</hi> this ſort of Aſſiſtance or Defence, though he ſhould <hi>call</hi> for it; and much leſs to <hi>offer</hi> it when <hi>unasked.</hi> For what were this indeed (as things now ſtand) but, out of an over-eager deſire of ſhewing an <hi>extravagant piece of Paſſive Obedience</hi> to out-act the <hi>Circumcellions</hi> themſelves; and aſſiſt barbarous <hi>Iriſh Tories,</hi> and <hi>French Dragoons,</hi> ſo as to enable them in the iſſue, to advance us to the too fondly affected Crown of an <hi>unwarrantable Martyrdom?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it (in the next place) ſuppoſed by any, that <hi>[Preaching and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for King</hi> James] are <hi>Duties</hi> indiſpenſably incumbent upon them, by vertue of their Allegiance? If ſo, I deſire them to conſider, that, ſuppoſing them <hi>ſuch,</hi> yet they can be no otherwiſe ſuch, than as all others are, that are ſo, by vertue of an <hi>Affirmative Precept,</hi> and ſo can be no otherwiſe obliging, (at leaſt, as to the circumſtances of their Actual Exerciſe) than as all things ſo commanded, are; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not bind us <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> (as the Schools ſpeak) That is, they are not neceſſarily to be done at <hi>all Times,</hi> whatever the conſequences of them may be; but the actual performance of them <hi>thus</hi> and <hi>thus,</hi> and at <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> ſeaſon, is to be governed by circumſtances; and where thoſe are ſuch, that the <hi>miſchief</hi> that will probably be done, is greater than the <hi>good</hi> that is likely to be conſequent on ſo doing; 'tis then <hi>unlawful</hi> to do them, becauſe <hi>unſeaſonable.</hi> This in <hi>general.</hi> But let us further view them <hi>particularly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As to <hi>[Preaching for K.</hi> J.] If <hi>Preaching up his preſent Cauſe,</hi> be meant thereby; and declaring all thoſe that are in Arms againſt him for their own Defence in <hi>Ireland,</hi> together with the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Forces</hi> ſent hence to aſſiſt them, <hi>Rebels,</hi> and incurring the penalty of <hi>Damnation</hi> for ſuch <hi>Reſiſtance;</hi> it is to make our ſelves <hi>Judges</hi> of a <hi>War,</hi> which we can never hope convincingly to prove unlawful, except upon the ſuppoſition of an <hi>unlimited Right</hi> in the <hi>Prince</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe univerſally of his Subjects, as to <hi>Religion, Laws, Liberties</hi> and <hi>Lives,</hi> as he pleaſeth; and the Duty of all that are within his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions tamely to ſuffer them all to be taken from them, upon the Obligation of the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance.</hi> And what can we hope for upon the preaching of this Doctrine (be it never ſo true) at this time of Day, under ſuch <hi>univerſal Prejudice</hi> againſt it, that can ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally make amends for the Inconveniences neceſſarily attendant
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56717:5"/> upon it; not only to <hi>our Perſons,</hi> from the Laws in being which (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the higheſt Penalties) forbid us ſo to do; but alſo, to the <hi>whole Nation,</hi> if our Doctrine ſhould (contrary to all rational probability) be entertained by any conſiderable numbers. For what could the Iſſue then be, but the raiſing of a bloody <hi>Civil War,</hi> in the bowels of it; and that <hi>War,</hi> (if it ſhould end in a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> on the ſide which by ſuch Preaching we aſſiſt,) conſequentially deſtructive to all thoſe dear Enjoyments, which, as we are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> are now ſecured to us under the Protection of the <hi>preſent Conſtitution,</hi> and the <hi>Forces</hi> raiſed by it? Beſides, that it would be a very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult thing for us, upon clear grounds, to determine the lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs of a War, the Juſtice whereof depends on ſo many <hi>Intrigues</hi> of <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> in the <hi>firſt Original</hi> of it (whence our meaſures muſt be taken) which Men of our Profeſſion cannot be throughly acquainted with the Truth or Falſhood of. For which of us can demonſtratively make out, againſt all contradiction, the <hi>Legitimacy</hi> of the P. of <hi>W.</hi> (though any of us in our own Judgments poſſibly might incline to that opinion, as I believe moſt of us once did, when he was ſo declared by the publick Authority then in being, and therefore, according to the direction of the Law in that caſe, we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted his Name, or Title at leaſt, in the publick Liturgy: (which yet we muſt be able to do, if we will undertake to condemn the <hi>invaſion</hi> of his <hi>now-Majeſty</hi> (then, <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange)</hi> to preſerve the Right his <hi>Princeſs</hi> had to the ſucceſſion, who (if the Child were Illegitimate, or Suppoſititious) was the <hi>next</hi> in the <hi>Royal Line</hi> to whom it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long) as unlawful? I ſpeak this, only to ſhew, how unmeet it is for us, in the Pulpit, to ground Doctrines of ſuch great importance to Salvation or Damnation to our People, upon ſuppoſal of ſuch things which we cannot <hi>Infallibly</hi> know to be <hi>true;</hi> or ſuch, which (as to matter of <hi>Fact)</hi> our People (not one it may be, to a thouſand, diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) will tell us to our teeth, as ſoon as we come out of the Pulpit, they never did, nor can believe. And undoubtedly our caution, in things of this nature, is not diſallowed, but rather encouraged, and directed by our <hi>Saviours</hi> Example; who, himſelf, in deciding a <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in a Caſe that concerned <hi>Caeſar,</hi> (by the very man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of delivering his Judgment therein) declared himſelf ſtudiouſly cautious of giving offence on both ſides: And though he determined it for the <hi>Emperor;</hi> yet, had we not an <hi>Inſtance</hi> of his own <hi>practice,</hi> to warrant the interpreting him that way, we could hardly gather it convincingly from his <hi>words</hi> alone. But, I ſuppoſe, I need not very earneſtly preſs this Point upon our Brethren, who by their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56717:6"/> practice generally have ſhewn their Caution therein: and ſeem there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to grant my Aſſertion, <hi>[That preaching for K.</hi> J. <hi>in the preſent Circumſtances is a piece of Allegiance, the obligation whereunto ceaſeth,</hi> q<hi rend="sup">d</hi> e. d.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next, as to <hi>[Praying for him]</hi> if it be a Duty, it is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed either in <hi>private,</hi> or <hi>publick,</hi> or <hi>both.</hi> And in both theſe, (ſuppoſing ſtill, that <hi>[for him]</hi> imports <hi>[for the ſucceſs of his preſent Arms]</hi> I doubt not, but to ſhew the <hi>ceſſation</hi> of this piece of Allegiance unto him too. For to do this in <hi>publick;</hi> it lies too much under the ſame inconveniences and diſadvantages, (and much more ſo,) with the former <hi>[of preaching for him,]</hi> for any of us to look upon our ſelves, as obliged by Allegiance ſo to do. And, as to our <hi>private Devotions,</hi> although any of us ſhould think it our Duty to <hi>pray</hi> for him in his <hi>perſonal</hi> circumſtances, to wit, for Gods ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his afflictions to him; his Converſion to the true Religion, and preſervation of him from evil accidents; nay, ſuppoſe ſome one think it his Duty, to go farther, and pray for his Reſtitution it ſelf: it contributes not much to the ſtating the Queſtion in hand, whether ſuch <hi>private</hi> ſentiments (as to the <hi>former</hi> ſorts) be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to be branches of the <hi>ceſſant</hi> Duty to K. <hi>J.</hi> or no. But as to the <hi>laſt, (his Reſtitution)</hi> it will certainly deſerve any <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſerious conſideration, whether in Conſcience, he can ſatisfie himſelf, even in his <hi>privateſt Devotions,</hi> to make his applications to Heaven, for the aſſiſting a Perſon to return to his <hi>former Eſtate,</hi> whoſe <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Inclinations</hi> too (except one could be certainly aſſured that he is become a true Convert, and ſo hath diſclaimed them) are directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>true Intereſt</hi> of that <hi>Religion,</hi> which (of all in the World,) he is perſwaded, that God whom he makes his Applications to, moſt approves and owns; and hath made it appear that he doth ſo, moſt remarkably of late, by ſo ſtrange a concatenation of <hi>Providential In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues</hi> throughout all <hi>Europe,</hi> for the ſecuring it, as hardly any Age can ſhew the like.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, for any Chriſtians of the <hi>Proteſtant Profeſſion,</hi> (and eſpecially of this <hi>Nation)</hi> to endeavour, though but by a ſecret wiſh, to obſtruct the progreſs of thoſe great Affairs, (which in the Proſpect of their probable Iſſue, promiſe the whole Proteſtant Cauſe, and chiefly in theſe Parts, ſo fair) were in <hi>all ſuch,</hi> in my Judgment, an high indication of a too <hi>ſtupid inſenſibleneſs</hi> of their <hi>deareſt concerns:</hi> but in <hi>any</hi> of <hi>us</hi> a too viſible <hi>implication</hi> beſides, of (that which is much worſe) an <hi>ungrateful longing</hi> to return back again to that <hi>Egyptian bondage,</hi> from which the Lord by ſo many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56717:6"/> of mercy hath ſo lately delivered us. At leaſt, it can certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, be no part of our Duty, to deprecate the continuation of that actual ſecurity from <hi>Romiſh Perſecution,</hi> which (whiles we our ſelves were bound up (by the influence of the Doctrines of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> upon our Conſciences,) from giving the leaſt <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> thereto) God alone by his <hi>mighty Hand and out-ſtretched Arm</hi> hath wrought for us.</p>
            <p>And now, I hope, I may take it for granted, that I have ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorily eſtabliſhed the verity of my <hi>ſecond Propoſition;</hi> both in the <hi>general,</hi> and alſo in all the <hi>particulars</hi> included in it: and therefore may proceed to the <hi>next.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. The <hi>third Propoſition,</hi> (which I think none will put me to prove, however, for the perfecting the train of conſequences in this Diſcourſe, it needs to be mentioned,) is this, <hi>[This ceſſant Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the former King, there is none elſe that viſibly claims, but K.</hi> W. <hi>and Q.</hi> M.] They are <hi>K. and Q. de facto,</hi> and exerciſe all <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> without any viſible oppoſition throughout this Nation. The <hi>Forts</hi> and the <hi>Forces,</hi> and the <hi>Royal Revenues</hi> of the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are wholly in their Hands. There is not, (in the Proverbial Phraſe of Scripture) <hi>a Dog that opens his Mouth</hi> againſt them. The Protection we have, in our <hi>Lives, Laws, Properties, Religious and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Liberties,</hi> we receive from the Influences of their Government: And therefore (as a farther branch of this Propoſition) it follows, <hi>[that we are to pay it to them.]</hi> For, ſurely, if <hi>[Protectio trahit Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giantiam,]</hi> (the Maxime of the Lawyers) be true in any caſe, it muſt needs be ſo in this; whiles, eſpecially, our Allegiance is at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty (as to him, who only can have any Pretenſion to it elſe) by the force of the <hi>firſt Propoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">IV. The <hi>fourth Propoſition</hi> is this. <hi>[The Allegiance which I may, (and much more, which I muſt) pay thoſe to whom it is proved due by the preceding Propoſitions, they may oblige me to promiſe: and what I may be obliged to promiſe, I cannot rationally refuſe to ſecure to them, if they demand it, by an Oath.]</hi> This Propoſition alſo, I think fit to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for (the Reaſon before-mentioned) the continuation of the threed of the Argument; but, I ſuppoſe, it likewiſe needs no Proof: it being a thing allowed in all humane converſation, as equitable to give ſuch <hi>ſecurity</hi> as our word, at leaſt, for all <hi>Debts;</hi> and that of an <hi>Oath,</hi> particularly, to thoſe <hi>(Superiours</hi> eſpecially) that will not take our <hi>bare word:</hi> and an <hi>Oath for confirmation,</hi> even the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſſerts to be the way to put an end to all ſtrifes, which in caſes of that nature may ariſe.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:56717:7"/>
            <p> And now I have done with the <hi>aſtructive part</hi> of this Diſcourſe, and affirmed both the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the Claim of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> to our <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and our <hi>Oath</hi> to give them Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it, in the preſent Circumſtances: There remains there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now, no more to be done, but the purfuance of the <hi>deſtructive part,</hi> or Demoliſhing the Strengths of our ſuppoſed Antagoniſts, by <hi>anſwering</hi> the <hi>Objections</hi> they do, or it may be conceived might make againſt my former Aſſertions. And this I ſhall endeavour by making good the <hi>Six Propoſitions</hi> following.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>[That whatever Right, according to their Principles, whom we have here to deal with, may yet remain to K.</hi> J. <hi>as to their Allegiance, is not by the Oath now required of them, diſclaimed; nor that of their preſent Majeſties aſſerted.]</hi> Sure I am, it is not <hi>expreſly,</hi> as appears by the <hi>words</hi> of it; there being nothing of <hi>Title</hi> or <hi>Right,</hi> the one, or the other way, mentioned therein. For the <hi>naming</hi> the Perſons to whom it is Sworn, <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> aſſerts only, the <hi>Factum,</hi> that they are actually ſo; affirming nothing of the <hi>Title,</hi> by which they are ſo. The <hi>Omiſſion</hi> whereof, (it being ſo expreſly and largely ſet forth in the <hi>former Oath of Allegiance)</hi> in this, is certainly a great Inſtance of the <hi>tenderneſs</hi> which the Compoſers thereof had for the known <hi>Principles</hi> of our <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> and <hi>Brethren;</hi> and deſigned (probably) for the preventing of this very <hi>Objection,</hi> which they foreſaw would with greateſt Difficulty be removed out of the way of thoſe Perſons, whom they ſo much deſired not to lay aſide out of the <hi>publick Settlement,</hi> which their ſeaſonable ſtanding in the Breach which our common Adverſaries had made in the Bulwarks of our <hi>Religion, Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> with their own great hazard, had given ſo great an Aſſiſtance to. But this <hi>Caution</hi> of theirs (as it unhappily falls out) hath not done what it was intended for. For it is ſtill objected, That the ſame is done <hi>implicitely,</hi> by the very <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>thing</hi> required, which was, by the forbearing thoſe <hi>explicite words,</hi> deſign'd to be avoided. For <hi>the Swearing Allegiance</hi> to <hi>One,</hi> denies it (in their Judgment) to all <hi>Others;</hi> and, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, this Oath implies the <hi>Renunciation</hi> of the <hi>former Oath,</hi> wherein the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>K.</hi> J. was aſſerted. To which I anſwer, that does not neceſſarily follow, if my <hi>former Hypotheſis</hi> be true; [That a meer <hi>actual Allegiance</hi> to <hi>another</hi> (which is all that this Oath obligeth us to) does not involve a <hi>Negation</hi> of the <hi>Perſon's Right</hi> who formerly had it; but only the <hi>Ceſſation</hi> of the <hi>Obligation</hi> thence ariſing, in the preſent Circumſtances, to <hi>act</hi> on his behalf.]</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56717:7"/>
            <p> I ſhall cloſe this <hi>Paragraph,</hi> with a <hi>Note,</hi> or two, out of the <hi>Reverend Dr.</hi> Sanderſon, who in his Book relating to the <hi>Caſe of the Engagement,</hi> declares it as his Judgment, <hi>[That where the words of a Promiſe may in fair Conſtruction be capable of a double meaning, ſo as to be taken in one ſenſe, they ſhall bind to more, and in another, to leſs; the Promiſer may make his juſt advantage of the Ambiguity, and take it in the ſame ſenſe which ſhall bind to the leſs. Becauſe the Faith to be given, is intended to the behoof of him to whom it is given; and therefore it concerneth him to take care that his meaning be expreſſed in ſuch words, as will ſufficiently manifeſt the Senſe to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of a reaſonable Man. Which if he neglect to do, no Law of Equity, or Prudence, bindeth the Promiſer, by an over-ſcrupulous Diligence, to lay a greater Obligation upon himſelf, than he needed to do.]</hi> Wherefore, if <hi>Allegiance,</hi> in this <hi>Oath,</hi> may fairly ſignifie either <hi>rightful Allegiance,</hi> or <hi>actual Allegiance</hi> only; if the words, <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> may be interpreted in the <hi>ſame Latitude;</hi> though it ſhould be ſuppoſed, that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers intended to ſtretch them to the <hi>more;</hi> nothing hinders the Swearer from interpreting them to the <hi>leſs</hi> rigorous Senſe. And ſo, this <hi>Objection,</hi> by his Judgment, will fall to the ground of it ſelf; and need give our Brethren no trouble.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>[That the Acts of Allegiance required by K.</hi> W. <hi>and Q.</hi> M. <hi>(of the Clergy at leaſt, in particular) contain in them nothing but what they may lawfully do, during the ceaſing Obligation of Obedience to K.</hi> J.] For thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> (according to the former Diſtribution) muſt be, either, <hi>Bearing of Arms at their Command, or aſſiſting the Forces they raiſe, by ſending in Militia Soldiers, or Payment of Taxes impoſed by them in the legal Methods, or Preaching or Praying for them.</hi> Now, the firſt of theſe, <hi>[bearing Arms in Perſon]</hi> no Clergy-man (as was before ſaid) can by Law be required to do; and therefore, they may be aſſured, that will not by <hi>their Majeſties</hi> (who are engaged to govern <hi>by Law)</hi> be demanded of them. And, as to the <hi>[fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing out ſuch of the ſtanding Militia appointed by Law, as their Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical or Temporal Revenues render them liable unto]</hi> as the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf juſtifies him that, by <hi>Command,</hi> doth it; ſo doth it by <hi>Penalties</hi> enforce thoſe that refuſe ſo to do. And ſo, that <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> will come under the Conſideration of the <hi>third</hi> Particular, <hi>[the Payment of Taxes in form of Law impoſed.]</hi> And the <hi>Payment</hi> of ſuch, may by the plenary <hi>Poſſeſſor</hi> of the <hi>Throne,</hi> be exacted from all Subjects, with all the <hi>Penalties</hi> incurred by refuſing, in caſe any one deny them. So that, (beſides the Liberty left any one to <hi>deny</hi> them, if he will run the <hi>hazard;)</hi> the <hi>quiet Payment</hi> of them amounts, indeed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56717:8"/> to no more (in a conſcientious, as well as prudent Conſideration) than the purchaſing our own eaſe, and compounding for a <hi>leſs Sum</hi> out of our Eſtates, with thoſe who may, upon refuſal, enforce from us a <hi>far greater.</hi> And we had, ſomewhat above Forty years ſince, a Caſe of the ſame nature, (though with far leſs colour of Law than this at preſent) wherein the doing of this, was univerſally allowed by the <hi>ſevereſt Aſſertors</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to K. <hi>C.</hi> I. and II. and therefore thence (in Reaſon, I think) be now leſs diſputable, (as to its lawfulneſs) to thoſe, who have received the <hi>ſtricteſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> they argue from in the preſent Circumſtances, from them; as will appear anon more largely in the handling of the Ninth <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet, withal, I conceive there is more to be ſaid, for ſuch <hi>Payments now,</hi> then at <hi>that Time</hi> there was; <hi>Partly,</hi> upon a <hi>Military</hi> Account; becauſe the <hi>end</hi> for which the <hi>Soldiery</hi> are to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained (though it be true, that in <hi>that</hi> War, a diſpoſſeſſed King was kept out of his Throne, as in <hi>this,)</hi> is far more juſtiſiable <hi>now,</hi> than at <hi>that time</hi> it was. For thoſe Arms were taken againſt a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Prince, and upon falſe Imputations of his <hi>Inclinations</hi> to Popery only; whereas, in this caſe thoſe Fears are really made good, both as to the <hi>Perſon</hi> and his <hi>Deſigns:</hi> And thoſe great Concerns of our <hi>Religion, Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> were only then concluded to be in danger, from <hi>remote Conſequences</hi> of ſome ſuſpicious Acts; which are now <hi>bare-facedly undermined.</hi> And partly, upon a <hi>Civil Account.</hi> The Laws have <hi>now</hi> their <hi>Free Courſe;</hi> whereas, <hi>then,</hi> all Law was trampled on by the conquering Party, either by Military Force, or by Arbitrary Courts. Whence, it is but meet, that that <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Adminiſtrators</hi> of it, ſhould be maintained by all thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Benefit and Advantage thereof. Nor is it, certainly, more inconſiſtent with the Obligations of any <hi>former Allegiance</hi> to <hi>pay</hi> for the Support of that Power that maintains me in my Right, than to <hi>appeal</hi> to its <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> for legal Relief againſt any that would deprive me thereof.</p>
            <p>The next Particular, <hi>[Preaching for them,]</hi> as the Perſons actually inveſted with Supreme Authority; can, (as required of us,) import no more than that which is our Duty at all Times by the <hi>Apoſtles Rule,</hi> Tit. 3. 1. The <hi>putting our People in mind to be ſubject to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and Powers, and to obey Magiſtrates:</hi> That is, actively, or paſſively, to <hi>obey</hi> thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> with the actual Adminiſtration whereof they are intruſted by the actual Poſſeſſion of that Supremacy whence they are derived. For as to the <hi>Title</hi> by which they hold that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56717:8"/> Supremacy, as they will not allow us to maintain that of the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed Prince</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit:</hi> So neither do they there require us to maintain their <hi>own.</hi> And it is well, this is not impoſed upon us, for if it were, we might have ſome colour to reluct; ſeeing it is juſtly diſputable, whether it were ever any part of our work, to <hi>diſpute</hi> the <hi>Titles of Princes</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> or (by <hi>aſſerting</hi> of them, in <hi>divided Congregations,)</hi> to occaſion them to be diſputed by others; whatever our private Judgment may be concerning them. For, if it were ſo, it is beyond all doubt to me, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> (or ſome one of them) would have left us ſuch certain Meaſures, as might have governed our <hi>own,</hi> and enabled us to ſatisfie all <hi>other</hi> Mens <hi>Judgments,</hi> in the Reſolution of ſuch various <hi>Caſes</hi> of Conſcience, as on that account, muſt, in all Nations, be ſuppoſed ever and anon to be ſtarted, from the different Pretenſions of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was it indeed, expedient, that our Lord ſhould <hi>clog</hi> that <hi>Religion,</hi> which he was firſt to recommend to the World (univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally prejudiced againſt it at that time upon other accounts) with ſuch a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as would have been more obnoxious to prejudice, than any of the reſt: Such, indeed, as would (probably) have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred all <hi>Princes jealous</hi> of the Progreſs of it; ſeeing it would have endangered the expoſing all their <hi>Titles</hi> to the Diſputes of its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and rendred them determinable, according to the Iſſue of them. A Prejudice which he hath wiſely prevented, by leaving his Followers ſome <hi>general Rules</hi> only, for their Deportment under ſuch <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> as they found in <hi>preſent Poſſeſſion;</hi> (who are the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2.) and thereby reconciled his <hi>Doctrine</hi> to the <hi>Intereſts</hi> of all actual Superiors, by what <hi>Title</hi> ſoever they hold their Authority.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As to <hi>[Praying for them]</hi> it ſeems but reaſonable, that ſeeing we cannot expect <hi>to lead quiet and peaceable Lives in all Godlineſs and Honeſty,</hi> while they that are poſſeſſed of Authority over us, lead <hi>unquiet</hi> and <hi>unpeaceable</hi> ones; therefore, (that being the <hi>means</hi> by God directed, as moſt proper and effectual to that <hi>end,)</hi> I cannot ſee, how it can be rationally doubted, whether we may, (nay rather, it follows, in my Judgment, that we muſt) make <hi>Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks, for Kings, and all that are in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> (and ſo, for their <hi>Majeſties,</hi> at preſent) which may, through Divine Grace, enable them to promote that <hi>end.</hi> And accordingly the People of God anciently, made no ſcruple to pray euen for the <hi>Kings of Babylon,</hi> who, by no other Claim then the Succeſs of their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56717:9"/> 
               <hi>Arms,</hi> could pretend to Juriſdiction over them, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 29. 7. And the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who alſo gives us the <hi>heads</hi> of the <hi>Petitions</hi> they offered on their behalf, abundantly teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,) for theſe <hi>Roman Emperors</hi> whoſe Title was never a jot better; as will anon be more fully made to appear.</p>
            <p>But I ſuppoſe, <hi>praying for the King and Queen in being,</hi> will, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, be allowed by thoſe with whom we have to deal; ſo long as the Petitions to be offered on their behalf, do not involve a <hi>ſenſe</hi> prejudicial to the <hi>right</hi> or <hi>ſafety</hi> of the <hi>Prince diſpoſſeſſed.</hi> But ſeeing the <hi>Clergy</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> in the publick Offices of <hi>Liturgy</hi> according to the Forms eſtabliſhed, are obliged to pray expreſly for the preſent King and Queen, <hi>that God will give them Victory over all their Enemies]</hi> and that God will <hi>[ſtrengthen them, that they may vanquiſh and overcome all their Enemies,] &amp;c.</hi> which they ſuppoſe muſt neceſſarily involve an <hi>Imprecation</hi> againſt the <hi>Prince</hi> attempting to recover his Throne by <hi>War:</hi> it therefore appears to them, to be inconſiſtent with the <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> they have ſworn to him to offer up theſe <hi>Requeſts</hi> (at leaſt) for the <hi>Princes Regnant,</hi> who keep him out of <hi>Poſſeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, I confeſs, ſeems the moſt <hi>difficult Objection</hi> to be anſwered (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the <hi>Principles</hi> of our <hi>Brethren</hi> before-mentioned to be allowed them,) in this whole Diſpute. Yet, it is not, in my opinion, incapable of a fair ſolution, from the very <hi>deſign</hi> and <hi>proper Genius</hi> of all enjoyned <hi>Forms</hi> of publick Devotion. For all ſuch, are not neceſſarily to be ſo worded, as to ſuit the <hi>private notions</hi> and <hi>ſentiments</hi> of every perſon who is to officiate or joyn in them, for this were impoſſible ever to be attained: but only to expreſs the <hi>ſenſe of the Church</hi> or any other Authority impoſing them; under whom the publick <hi>Adminiſtrator,</hi> in the uſe of them, only lends a <hi>mouth,</hi> to aſſiſt the ſtated Devotion of the Congregation, wherein he oſſiciates, according to their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meaſures. So, when in the <hi>Form</hi> for the <hi>Burial of the Dead,</hi> we ſeem to ſpeak with confidence of <hi>Gods taking to himſelf the Soul of</hi> ſuch an one <hi>our Brother,</hi> and profeſs our <hi>certain hope of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Eternal Life,</hi> with implication of the <hi>parties ſhare</hi> therein, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whoſe eternal Eſtate it may be we are not perſonally ſatisfied: I take it to be a fair anſwer to the objection thence raiſed; That we <hi>only utter the ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> on whoſe behalf we therein officiate; which, ſo long as the <hi>Perſon deceaſed</hi> at any Time dies in her <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> does by us, diſmiſs him out of the World, with this <hi>fair Teſtimony</hi> of her univerſal <hi>charity</hi> to ſuch as are members thereof. And it deſerves upon this account, in my poor Judgment, to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, whether ſuch a <hi>Form,</hi> be not more expedient to be continued,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56717:9"/> notwithſtanding that ſuppoſed inconvenience; than to expoſe all Miniſters to a greater, by leaving them a liberty to make what <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions</hi> they judge fit, betwixt neighbour and neighbour, according to their apprehenſions concerning their Eternal Eſtate, by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>diſtinct forms</hi> accommodated to them. But this by the by. The <hi>Prejudice</hi> of ſome Perſons alſo, who are diſaffected to our <hi>Litany,</hi> againſt the <hi>expreſſions,</hi> wherein we <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>[all that travel by Land or by Water]</hi> and for <hi>[all Women labouring with Child,]</hi> and for <hi>[all Priſoners and Captives,]</hi> becauſe, (as they weakly argue,) in theſe <hi>general words</hi> are comprehended <hi>evil Spirits,</hi> that <hi>compaſs the Earth;</hi> and <hi>Pirats from</hi> Tunis <hi>or</hi> Algier <hi>that infeſt the Seas,</hi> and <hi>Women preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by Whoredom;</hi> and <hi>Felons, and Traytors laid up in Goal for their Crimes,</hi> &amp;c. This prejudice, I ſay, muſt be taken off by no other Anſwer than ſuch as this, That theſe particulars, do not fall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>deſign</hi> of <hi>publick Devotions,</hi> according whereto <hi>general expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> muſt be underſtood, as they are intended, with relation only to ſuch Perſons as are ſuppoſed rationally to be included in the charity of the Church compoſing and enjoyning thoſe Forms: in which <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> it is very uncharitably imagin'd, that <hi>Devils,</hi> and <hi>Turklſh Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats,</hi> and <hi>Harlots,</hi> and <hi>Rogues,</hi> and <hi>Traitors,</hi> are intentionally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted.</p>
            <p>And by the ſame <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> proportionably muſt thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> for <hi>Princes,</hi> be interpreted. Certainly, when <hi>our Reformers</hi> at the firſt, compoſed thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> for the uſe of this Church; they never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſuit them exactly to all the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> emerging in all the uncertain <hi>Accidents</hi> of <hi>Government:</hi> againſt which, becauſe they could not certainly be foreſeen, no humane Wiſdom could certainly provide. But they had in <hi>proſpect</hi> only, the <hi>ſucceſſive continuation</hi> of <hi>actual Governours</hi> intruſted for the peace and ſafety of the Nation: for the preſervation whereof, it is neceſſary to deſire of God, that the <hi>Forces</hi> by which they muſt ſecure to us theſe great Bleſſings may be <hi>actually Victorious</hi> againſt <hi>all</hi> ſuch as are <hi>real Enemies</hi> to that <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity;</hi> and therefore in general Terms they direct us ſo to <hi>pray.</hi> Now, to include a <hi>particular Perſon</hi> diſputing the Right of the Crown, in this <hi>general Petition;</hi> muſt ſuppoſe him to be an <hi>actual Enemy</hi> to this Nation either by a <hi>wrong Title,</hi> or an <hi>evil Deſign,</hi> or <hi>both:</hi> and whoever is <hi>really</hi> ſo, though he ſhould be <hi>included,</hi> hath no wrong; and if he be not ſo, it is inconſiſtent with the opinion we ought to have of the <hi>charity</hi> of our Church, to imagine him to be therein <hi>included.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56717:10"/>
            <p> It is, herein, farther obſervable, that theſe <hi>clauſes</hi> are ſuch, as hath been intimated before, as were not put in now <hi>firſt,</hi> in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar favour to their <hi>preſent Majesties:</hi> but are part of the ſame <hi>Form</hi> which hath been uſed for all their <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> ſince the <hi>Reformation.</hi> Nor is there any <hi>Petition peculiar</hi> to them, required of us to offer to God, which all <hi>Princes</hi> that ſhall ſway this Scepter to all ſucceeding Generations are not alike entituled to: Now would our diſſatisfied Brethren, think it fit to have a Precedent made for ſucceeding Ages, by the permitting ſuch an omiſſion in the publick Liturgy in favour to the pretenſions of K. <hi>J.</hi> now? For may not ſuch an <hi>Example</hi> be urged, or is it not liable to be urged in ſome future competition af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter K. <hi>J.</hi> his death, (and who knows, what may be hereafter?) upon the <hi>Proteſtant Clergy;</hi> ſuppoſing any future <hi>Prince Regnant</hi> ſhall fall out to be of the <hi>Romiſh Perſuaſion,</hi> and engaged by arms to maintain his Poſſeſſion, and keep out a more rightful <hi>Proteſtant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor?</hi> Suppoſing then, the <hi>ſame Petitions</hi> ſtill by <hi>Law</hi> to be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our publick <hi>Liturgy,</hi> under ſuch Circumſtances: can we think, it would look well, for the credit or ſafety of our Religion, if any conſiderable Part of our <hi>Proteſtant Clergy</hi> ſhould make it a ſcruple of Conſcience to uſe them in their publick Devotions out of favour to Him whoſe Title they judged the better? Nay, let us bring the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> of ſuch an <hi>Event</hi> in our thoughts a little nearer. Suppoſe (which was not impoſſible to have ſo fallen out) that K. <hi>J.</hi> had made the Throne vacant by Death, before his <hi>Preſent Majeſty</hi> (then only <hi>P. of Orange)</hi> landed, and another <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> (by Conqueſt, or ſome other diſputable way,) had filled it, before he could appear upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ground with his <hi>Army;</hi> and had been as clearly and as long poſſeſſed of it, as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> now hath been; I ask, would it have paſſed for a fair <hi>Plea,</hi> for the denyal of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to ſuch a <hi>poſſeſſed Prince,</hi> that we could not in Conſcience give it, becauſe we ſhould be obliged in our Liturgy to pray for <hi>Victory</hi> againſt the <hi>excluded Prince,</hi> and his Army, then ready to invade us, for the Defence of his <hi>own,</hi> and the <hi>Princeſſes</hi> Title? Let us but ſoberly think, what would have been the Conſequence of ſuch a Principle in thoſe Circumſtances, and apply it to the preſent Caſe.</p>
            <p>But to ſhew, farther, the fairneſs of my <hi>Interpretation</hi> of the ſaid Petitions; I will try, next, whether I cannot conclude the probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it, from the very practice of thoſe <hi>Reverend Perſons</hi> themſelves, with whom our preſent diſpute lies. It is not long ſince, that the whole <hi>Clergy</hi> of this Land made their Prayers, in the ſame Terms for K. <hi>J.</hi> Now, it is hardly to be imagined, that any <hi>Miniſter,</hi> yea, or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:56717:10"/> 
               <hi>Member</hi> of this Church, could offer up theſe Requeſts men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for him, without great reluctancy in himſelf (eſpecially in his later Days) but with ſome ſuch, (and probably, in moſt of them the ſame) <hi>reſtriction</hi> or <hi>limitation</hi> ſuppoſed. For elſe, all that joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, muſt be concluded, to have <hi>prayed againſt</hi> all the <hi>Proteſtants Intereſt in the World,</hi> (who, it is evident, were enemies againſt K. <hi>J.</hi> and <hi>his Religion,)</hi> if they ſhould at any Time, in never ſo juſt a War, <hi>defend</hi> themſelves againſt him by <hi>Arms.</hi> Such <hi>Clergy-men</hi> therefore (who were generally, all thoſe of this Church) who then uſed this <hi>General Form,</hi> cannot fairly come off, from the ſuſpicious <hi>implication</hi> thereof; but upon an <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of this nature, <hi>that thoſe Petitions in that Juncture intended no more, then the ſubduing ſuch Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his, as together with the deſtruction of his Perſon,</hi> ſhould at any Time deſign the ſubverſion of his <hi>Government</hi> as <hi>legally eſtabliſhed,</hi> or the <hi>ruin of this Nation,</hi> or ſome other of a like import. Let then, our <hi>Reverend Brethren</hi> allow the like ſuppoſal of ſutable <hi>reſtrictions</hi> and <hi>limitations</hi> in the <hi>preſent caſe,</hi> to theſe <hi>general expreſſions;</hi> and they will not find it ſo difficult a matter, to reconcile themſelves to the uſe of them on the behalf of their <hi>preſent Majeſties,</hi> which they (with others) uſed ſo long without ſcruple for their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To give a full confirmation to my aforeſaid <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> I think that <hi>clauſe</hi> in the laſt <hi>Act of</hi> Uniformity <hi>[That in all thoſe Prayers, Litanies and Collects, which do any way relate to the King, Queen or Royal Progeny, their Names be altered and changed from time to time, and fitted to the preſent occaſion,</hi> (undoubtedly, they that made this <hi>Proviſo,</hi> mean the circumſtances of the <hi>King or Queen Regnant,</hi> after any change,) <hi>according to the direction of lawful Authority;]</hi> does much conduce thereunto. It appears, that the ſame <hi>Form</hi> is to be uſed, by this <hi>clauſe</hi> ſtill, whatever occaſion requires the alteration of the <hi>Names:</hi> for the <hi>Proviſo</hi> is only made for the alteration of theſe. Suppoſe then the <hi>Throne</hi> at any time vacant by death; and a <hi>competiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> ariſe concerning the Succeſſion, where, during this <hi>Compoſition,</hi> is <hi>this lawful Authority,</hi> but in the <hi>actual Succeſſor,</hi> who enters upon the void Throne, and is ſo far <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> of it, as to ſend forth his <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> all through the Nation, to inſert ſuch <hi>Names</hi> as ſuit his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances? Whence, I further demand, Whether the <hi>Clergy</hi> may not, yea, whether they muſt not take ſuch a Mandate as ſufficient warrant, to uſe this <hi>Form,</hi> in the very paſſages under Diſpute, with ſuch <hi>alterations?</hi> And if ſo, then though the <hi>Perſon excluded</hi> in the Competition, ſhould chance to have the <hi>beſt Title</hi> of the <hi>two;</hi> yet
<pb facs="tcp:56717:11"/> the <hi>preſent Poſſeſſors</hi> command is valid againſt him; and the point in Diſpute is evidently gained, <hi>That the Clergy are (according to the Law it ſelf) to be governed by the Prince Regnant, in the particularities of theſe Petitions:</hi> and we may, and ought to offer them up for Him, and whom he <hi>Names,</hi> by Name, when required. But, (to put an end at laſt, to this <hi>long Section)</hi> and proceed. I ſay, Seventhly,</p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>[That the Principles of</hi> Non-reſiſtance <hi>and</hi> Paſſive Obedience, <hi>ſo far as (for ought I can ſee) they are owned by the Church of</hi> England, <hi>oblige us not, in our preſent circumſtances, to deny the giving, or ſwearing Allegiance to K.</hi> W. <hi>and Q.</hi> M.]</p>
            <p>That they <hi>do not,</hi> may be fairly argued, from the want of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>proof,</hi> from thoſe that ſay they <hi>do,</hi> taken out of any <hi>publick Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents</hi> or <hi>Records</hi> extant, which legally include the whole <hi>Body</hi> of this Church, to that purpoſe. And by ſuch indeed, and ſuch only muſt all things, which are alledged to be the <hi>Doctrines of this Church,</hi> be proved to be ſo. For, if we admit any other <hi>Evidence</hi> in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; we ſhall have much ado to vindicate our Church, in many great Points in Controverſie betwixt us and the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> together with our other <hi>Adverſaries;</hi> who, from the writings of <hi>particular Doctors</hi> in it, <hi>charge</hi> it with many <hi>abſurd</hi> and <hi>falſe Aſſertions.</hi> And therefore, it hath been always in ſuch caſes, the approved courſe of her learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Champions,</hi> to put the <hi>Adverſaries</hi> upon <hi>proof,</hi> that thoſe Doctrines which they charge on her, are her own, from her <hi>Articles, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, Liturgy,</hi> &amp;c. Let therefore, any of thoſe that endeavour to faſten upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as her Doctrines, any of thoſe high Notions concerning <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> which they pretend to have learned from her; firſt, State the <hi>Queſtions</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to them, according to their <hi>own Judgments:</hi> and then produce ſuch Proofs of the full concurrence of this Church with them, out of thoſe Books, or any other evidences of like nature; which muſt firſt be done, before they can rationally argue thence, the inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> with them as ſuch. And let none, (as ſome <hi>confident Authors</hi> of late have done) call the <hi>wild</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Opinions</hi> of ſome ſingular <hi>deſigning</hi> and <hi>intereſted Divines,</hi> like themſelves, accommodated to the <hi>guſt</hi> of a <hi>Court-Faction,</hi> the Doctrines of this Church. A thing, wherein they have done their <hi>Mother</hi> very ill ſervice, whiles (labouring to qualifie her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Principles to the humour of the diſpoſers of thoſe Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they ſought for) they were not only themſelves made meer <hi>Inſtruments</hi> and <hi>Tools</hi> of a <hi>Jeſuitical Faction;</hi> but endangered alſo the the whole Church and Nation, by raiſing <hi>Prerogative</hi> ſo high, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56717:11"/> when it fell into ill hands to manage it, they took encouragement thence to trample down our <hi>Religion, Laws, and Liberties;</hi> as ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing us all, a company of <hi>tame Animals,</hi> made only to bear what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever burdens they laid on us, and withal the occaſion too inſolently to reproach us with our <hi>ſuppoſed Principles</hi> of <hi>Paſſivity,</hi> whiles they gave us ſo many occaſions to practiſe them: as <hi>Julian</hi> once made uſe of our Saviours true Doctrine of <hi>not reſiſting evil,</hi> in the very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances whereby he explains it, in a proud <hi>Scoff</hi> to thoſe whom he maliciouſly perſecuted.</p>
            <p>It is true, indeed, that in the <hi>Declaration,</hi> which the Parliament (at the Return of K. <hi>Charles</hi> II.) after their having been ſo long exaſperated with the conſequents of the War made with his <hi>Father,</hi> under colour of a <hi>Parliamentary right</hi> in the <hi>Militia</hi> of this Kingdom; (and pleaded for by thoſe that defended their cauſe that oppoſed him, with an unuſual novel Diſtinction, of <hi>taking Arms by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt his Perſon, and thoſe that were commiſſioned by him;)</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired all the <hi>Clergy</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and all in publick Truſt (for the greater ſecurity of the <hi>reſtored King,</hi> whom they thought then they could never do too much for) to condemn that <hi>Poſition</hi> as it had been taught, as <hi>Traiterous</hi> and <hi>abominable:</hi> and to profeſs for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they held it <hi>unlawful upon any Pretence whatſoever to take up Arms againſt the King and thoſe that are Commiſſioned by him:</hi> and therein, (as alſo in another <hi>Act</hi> concerning the <hi>Militia)</hi> declared their own Judgments in thoſe Points more fully than had ever, by ſo publick a Body, been done before. But whether <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> may be taken for ſufficient <hi>Expoſitions</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>this Church,</hi> all thoſe who are unſatisfied in the matter of that <hi>Declaration,</hi> may poſſibly call in <hi>Queſtion,</hi> and (for the moſt part) reſolve it in the <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> For my Part, I will do neither: but take it for what proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly it was, the Doctrine of ſo many of the Church then repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Convocation</hi> as were conſulted in the drawing up that <hi>Form:</hi> and becauſe the <hi>whole Convocation</hi> ſubſcribed it, (at leaſt, after the Law paſſed) as did alſo the generality of the <hi>Clergy</hi> after them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it to have been the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> at that Time, in the ſenſe wherein they that impoſed it, underſtood it. But ſurely, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Parliament</hi> nor the <hi>Clergy</hi> in <hi>Convocation,</hi> ever intended thereby to give any <hi>King of England</hi> ſo uncontrollable a Power of breaking down all <hi>banks</hi> of <hi>Law,</hi> as to make the whole <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> meer <hi>Tenants at Will</hi> to Him for their <hi>Religion, Property, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> yea, and their very <hi>Lives</hi> themſelves, and leave the Subject no legal Remedy againſt the moſt illegal Violences. They did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56717:12"/> undoubtedly mean by <hi>[thoſe that are Commiſſioned by the King]</hi> thoſe only that are <hi>Commiſſioned as our Laws allow, and to ſuch intents and purpoſes as may conſiſt with them.</hi> We cannot ſurely, imagine them to be ſo beſotted, as to reſign all thoſe dear Intereſts at once into the Hands of a <hi>Popiſh Army</hi> raiſed on purpoſe to deſtroy and root them out altogether: which appears by what followed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in a ſubſequent <hi>Parliament,</hi> where in the whole Eſtates there aſſembled perceiving that ſome ill-deſigning Perſons took occaſion from that <hi>Declaration</hi> to mount the Points of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> to an extravagant height, (to which at laſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Project, they arrived;) in hope, by a <hi>Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor</hi> to bring about thoſe evil ends: took a wiſe courſe to prevent the miſchief by impoſing ſuch a <hi>Teſt</hi> upon all <hi>Commiſſioned Officers,</hi> as excluded all <hi>Papiſts</hi> from being in <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> and if they ſhould at any Time be ſo, declared their <hi>Commiſſions void,</hi> and all they did in purſuance of them <hi>null.</hi> That former <hi>Parliamentary Doctrine,</hi> (therefore) is expounded by this after commentary upon it, from the <hi>ſame Authority</hi> which firſt expreſly taught it.</p>
            <p>But as to the <hi>proper Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> declared by themſelves in any <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Record</hi> extant, it is vain to ſeek for any reſolution in this matter. They no where, (that I can learn) give us any Determination of theirs, concerning the <hi>Titles to Crowns,</hi> the <hi>extent</hi> of <hi>Prerogative</hi> in the <hi>Prince,</hi> the meaſures of that <hi>Subjection</hi> which <hi>Allegiance</hi> includes, nor concerning the <hi>extent</hi> of its <hi>obligation,</hi> or the <hi>change,</hi> which upon the various <hi>Turns</hi> of <hi>Providence,</hi> may, or may not, be made therein. Only, as to <hi>Kings and Queens actually in Being,</hi> they <hi>deny</hi> it at any time <hi>lawful to Rebel againſt them, whatever they perſonally are, or what Religion ſoever they are of, and by force of Arms to endeavour to diſpoſſeſs and deſtroy them.</hi> Of ſuch Doctrines as theſe all the <hi>Homilies of Obedience,</hi> and <hi>againſt wilful Rebellion,</hi> are full. And by theſe Doctrines, <hi>all Princes</hi> actually poſſeſſed of the Throne are alike ſecure, as to any danger, from the Church of <hi>England.</hi> So that as to the <hi>Queſtions</hi> and <hi>Caſes of Conſcience,</hi> which relate to our <hi>preſent Circumſtances,</hi> it will prove an undertaking too hard, I ſuppoſe, for any Perſon to make the Doctrines of this Church concerning <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> to comply with that tame ſubmiſſion to an <hi>unbounded Prerogative,</hi> trampling, by unpreſidented <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> all <hi>Laws</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, which ſome Men (as I before intimated) have of late vented under her Name. And I ſuppoſe alſo, that the moſt Reverend, the <hi>Archbiſhop of Canterbury,</hi> the <hi>right Reverend Biſhops,</hi> with others of the <hi>Reverend Clergy,</hi> and the worthy <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Fellows</hi> of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:56717:12"/> College, were not wanting to their Duty of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> nor miſunderſtood the Doctrine of th is Church, when they ſo notably pleaded their <hi>Right in Law,</hi> againſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations</hi> of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation</hi> to the utmoſt, and thereby, and by their <hi>Sufferings</hi> for it, ſtopped the career thereof from its triumphant Progreſs throughout the Nation, and as to what other <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> hath ſince been made by a too <hi>unreaſonably provoked Nation,</hi> together with the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of it: How far, the <hi>natural Duty of Self-preſervation,</hi> even by <hi>Arms</hi> againſt <hi>outragious illegal Violence,</hi> and the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> in all <hi>Political Societies</hi> governed by <hi>Laws,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the <hi>fundamental Conſtitution</hi> of this <hi>Monarchy, &amp;c.</hi> pleaded on their behalf, will juſtifie thoſe that have had an hand in it, in ſuch a caſe of <hi>extream neceſſity:</hi> I cannot find determinable from any publick Records of this Church. To be ſure, it much concerns not our <hi>diſſatisfied Brethrens Caſe;</hi> that it ſhould be determined, ſeeing none of them have any way contributed to any ſuch <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> hitherto; and are not (as I think I have ſufficiently evidenced above) endangered for the future, by any thing which this <hi>Oath</hi> obligeth them unto, to loſe the Honour and Comfort of keeping the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> inviolate, to the utmoſt extent of it, as ſtated by themſelves.</p>
            <p>And, as to that of <hi>Paſſive Obedience;</hi> it can ſurely be no farther a Duty in this Caſe, than <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> is: for this is the neceſſary <hi>conſequent</hi> of that: whom I muſt in no ſort <hi>reſiſt,</hi> I muſt, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, <hi>ſubmit</hi> to <hi>ſuffer</hi> under, in whatſoever he lays upon me: and on the other ſide, ſo far as I may <hi>lawfully reſiſt,</hi> I am not bound to <hi>ſuffer.</hi> As in the Caſe of the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Reverend Perſons</hi> but now mentioned; who took ſhelter in the <hi>Law</hi> ſo far as it would be allowed them, and then only <hi>ſuffered,</hi> when it would ſtand them in no farther ſtead. For otherwiſe, it ſeems too high a ſtrain of <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> and more than <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> requires, for any one patiently to quit the <hi>Defence</hi> which <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> allow him, yea, and the very <hi>Laws</hi> themſelves which allow them to him; that he may gain an Opportunity to exerciſe his <hi>Patience</hi> under <hi>illegal Violence:</hi> and to ſeek an occaſion of undergoing thoſe Sufferings a Mans ſelf, which our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf allows him, if there be no other way open, at leaſt, by <hi>flight,</hi> to eſcape.</p>
            <p>Nay, I will go yet one ſtep farther in this caſe; and allow the Parties, that under <hi>ſhelter</hi> of a <hi>Royal Commiſſion,</hi> ſeek a Man's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to have, in ſome Juncture, all the ſtrength of <hi>Law</hi> on their ſide; and withall, ſuppoſe him that is ſo endangered, to be,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56717:13"/> by Providence, placed in theſe Circumſtances, wherein he is for the preſent (though by an <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>illegal Force)</hi> preſerved from <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Hands.</hi> Let, therefore, Famous <hi>London-Derry</hi> be the deſigned <hi>Scene</hi> of a <hi>Popiſh Perſecution;</hi> where a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> by his Habitation, and the Obligation of his other Circumſtances, reſides: And is, by the making the City a <hi>Garriſon</hi> (without his contributing thereunto in the leaſt, that we may lay the caſe as wholly and intirely <hi>Paſſive</hi> as may be) ſafe, while he remains there. This Man is ſo far poſſeſſed with a Conſcientious Principle of <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> that (even in theſe Circumſtances) he dares not take up <hi>Arms</hi> with the <hi>Garriſon</hi> when Beleagured (as lately) to maintain the <hi>Walls,</hi> and therein, his own <hi>Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. againſt K. <hi>J.</hi> and his <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Army,</hi> as thinking the <hi>Defendants Rebels,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> entirely on the <hi>Beſiegers</hi> ſide. I would fain learn, now, whether in this Caſe, it be not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, (even for a Man ſo <hi>Principled)</hi> to accept of the <hi>Protection,</hi> which (without his ſeeking) his <hi>Habitation</hi> gives him; be the Hands which defend it what they will, even whatever K. <hi>J.</hi> himſelf would call them, may he not, for the preſent, exerciſe the more <hi>Beneficial</hi> ſort of <hi>Patience,</hi> by <hi>ſuffering</hi> himſelf, though ſore againſt his Inclination, to be <hi>protected</hi> (againg <hi>ſuffering</hi> more grievouſly by the <hi>Popiſh Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers,</hi> if they could get him into their hands) by the ſuppoſed <hi>Rebel-Governour,</hi> and his <hi>Garriſon?</hi> If not, what is he obliged to do? Is there any, who will judge it to be his Duty, by the obligation of his Principle of <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> to endeavour to raiſe a <hi>Tumult</hi> within againſt the Governour, or to <hi>betray</hi> that Power that illegally protects him, by entertaining Spies from the <hi>Beſiegers,</hi> or ſending them <hi>Intelligence?</hi> You will ſay (it may be) this is more than <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> this is <hi>Action</hi> rather. But ſtill, this is in order to the <hi>Paſſivity</hi> he thinks he <hi>owes</hi> the <hi>Law.</hi> Or is he (to take a <hi>ſhorter</hi> courſe to it) to <hi>withdraw himſelf</hi> out of his <hi>Protection,</hi> and deliver himſelf into the hands of the <hi>Loyal Beſiegers?</hi> I confeſs, I ſhould think (to the contrary) that he ſhould rather thank God, and <hi>even Rebels,</hi> for his <hi>Protection,</hi> lye quiet under his ſhelter whilſt he may; and content himſelf with his <hi>diſpoſitive Preparation</hi> to undergo what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may befall him with others, in caſe the <hi>Garriſon</hi> come at laſt to be taken; and ſo expect the reward of his Patience from that God, whoſe <hi>call</hi> of unavoidable Providence, and no <hi>Procurement</hi> of his own, expoſeth him to it.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe, (after all this is ſaid to weaken it) that our <hi>higheſt Brethrens</hi> Notion, concerning <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> ſhould ſtand firm, in reference to K. <hi>J.</hi> and <hi>thoſe Commiſſioned by him:</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56717:13"/> yet am I ſtill at a loſs, how (according to a <hi>Paper</hi> lately Printed, containing the <hi>Dying Declaration</hi> of the <hi>Right Reverend the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Chicheſter) even that can rationally be improved, to the rendring the preſent <hi>Oath of Allegiance to K.</hi> W. <hi>and Q.</hi> M. unlawful. Seeing, upon the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> I have before laid, do, and I hope, ſufficiently proved the <hi>Allegiance</hi> promiſed by it, includes nothing which (according to it) a Man, even of thoſe Principles, may not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pay: and binds him not to contribute more, to the hinderance of that Power from being Paramount, under which he thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf rather obliged to <hi>ſuffer</hi> than to <hi>obey</hi> this that protects him, then what may by <hi>legal Proceſs</hi> be <hi>forced</hi> from him: And what <hi>Force</hi> in ſuch Circumſtances <hi>cauſeth,</hi> it doth withall <hi>excuſe;</hi> as you will ſee more anon, when I have diſpatched one <hi>Propoſition</hi> more, which is this:</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>That the Law of the Land, juſtifies the Subject in the Payment of his actual Allegiance to the actual Poſſeſſor of the Throne, though wrongfully, whilſt he continues to be ſo poſſeſſed,. though at the ſame time there be another rightful K. out of Poſſeſſion.]</hi> This, I confeſs, is not within my <hi>Province</hi> to prove ſo ſtrongly and convincingly, as ſome learned Men of the long Robe have undertaken to do, and (moſt think) have done beyond Contradiction. Nor will I enlarge this Diſcourſe to ſuch a Bulk, as the <hi>Tranſcription</hi> of what hath been ſaid by them to that purpoſe would ſwell it to: But I ſhall content my ſelf with the bare mention of one Famous <hi>Statute</hi> (that of 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.) which highly <hi>Indemnifies</hi> all Perſons that <hi>aſſiſt the King in being</hi> (even with <hi>Arms)</hi> againſt him that is <hi>King de Jure.</hi> The reaſon whereof muſt needs be, that the <hi>Makers</hi> of that <hi>Statute</hi> looked on ſuch Perſons, either as <hi>Innocent,</hi> ſuppoſing them under a <hi>Force;</hi> or as doing their <hi>Duty,</hi> if <hi>voluntarily</hi> complying with the Divine Providence placing him on the Throne, while he ſits there. This, in the next <hi>Propoſition,</hi> I ſhall farther evince from <hi>Practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>[That the ſtouteſt Aſſertors of the Principles of indiſpenſable Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, Non-reſiſtance, and Paſſive Obedience, formerly have ſo far complied with the Supream Powers in actual Poſſeſſion, as this Paper pleads for now; and been juſtified in ſo doing, by the moſt learned and judicious Caſuiſts then living.]</hi> For, as to the <hi>Payment</hi> of <hi>Military Taxes</hi> to the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> and the ſeveral <hi>Models</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> that ſucceeded or interloped with them in K. <hi>C.</hi> I. and K. <hi>C.</hi> II's time; appearing at their <hi>Bars</hi> on their <hi>Summons, compounding for their Eſtates</hi> at the Rates they impoſed, <hi>Suing</hi> and being <hi>Sued</hi> in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56717:14"/> their <hi>Courts; Addreſſing</hi> to them, upon occaſion, in the <hi>Terms</hi> they directed, and by the <hi>Titles</hi> they aſſumed; yea, and (more than all this) ſubſcribing an <hi>Engagement,</hi> to be <hi>true</hi> and <hi>Faithful</hi> to them, that is, to pay them all that which we call <hi>Allegiance:</hi> Who is there that lived in thoſe Times, who knows not, that the generality both of the Clergy and Laity, who went under the Name of <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> and high <hi>Royaliſts,</hi> did comply with the <hi>prevalent Faction</hi> (by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Name they exerciſed the <hi>Sovereign Authority)</hi> ſome more, and ſome leſs, as their Circumſtances obliged them, through all the Varieties of that Government? All which <hi>Acts</hi> are judged to be, in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and in <hi>ordinary Caſes, Treaſonable Acts;</hi> and (by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) high Breaches of <hi>Allegiance;</hi> and were no way juſtifiable, but by the Words, or Reaſon (at leaſt) of the <hi>Statute</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. And yet he is a great <hi>Stranger</hi> in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who knows not alſo, that they were juſtified in ſo doing, by the Determinations of the ableſt <hi>Lawyers</hi> and the moſt eminent <hi>Caſuiſts;</hi> and eſpecially (of the later ſort) by the Writings of that incomparable Maſter in Theology, Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> afterwards (for his Loyal Service in thoſe times to his Majeſty, K. <hi>C.</hi> II.) advanced to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> Now, theſe things they could not have done, (eſpecially with the allowance of ſuch Spiritual Guides,) had the <hi>Principles</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> been then underſtood to be ſo rigorous in. Matters of this Nature, as thoſe of our preſent <hi>diſſatisfied Brethren,</hi> in their <hi>Caſuiſtical Divinity,</hi> are. The very <hi>Engagement,</hi> but now mentioned, which was then generally ſwallowed by thoſe that would have taken it very ill to have been thought no true Sons of the Chureh of <hi>England,</hi> (and divers of whom, were notwithſtanding, even when rigorous Conformity was at the higheſt, after the <hi>Return</hi> of K. <hi>C.</hi> II. thought worthy to be advanced to ſome of the moſt <hi>eminent Biſhopricks,</hi> and other <hi>Dignities</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;)</hi> was thought then (by thoſe that by it loſt their Places, out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their Duty to the King) to be <hi>unlawful,</hi> as being a <hi>new Promiſe</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers:</hi> and if it were ſo, (as they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended) was certainly ſuch an one, <hi>with a witneſs,</hi> (as we uſe to ſpeak) in compariſon of that which the <hi>preſent Oath</hi> requires. For the Obedience by this <hi>Oath</hi> required, is expreſſed by its proper <hi>Name,</hi> the <hi>Notation</hi> whereof imports a <hi>limited legal Obedience</hi> only; whereas the words <hi>[True and Faithful]</hi> in the <hi>Engagement,</hi> ran ſo large, as not to inſinuate the leaſt Intimation of any <hi>legal Bounds</hi> to the Duty promiſed. <hi>This</hi> is, to a <hi>K.</hi> and <hi>Q. that,</hi> to a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> this, can only (at the worſt) be ſuppoſed to be Injurious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56717:14"/> to the Right of <hi>one King</hi> by transferring it to another: Whereas <hi>that,</hi> overthrew the <hi>Throne</hi> it ſelf; and deſtroyed the <hi>Right</hi> of all <hi>future Kings,</hi> yea, and <hi>Parliaments</hi> too, by excluding out of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment <hi>them,</hi> and the <hi>whole Houſe of Lords.</hi> And, by conſequence, it is probable, in an high Degree, that thoſe who allowed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the <hi>taking of that Engagement,</hi> in the Circumſtances of thoſe Times, as not inconſiſtent with the Principles of this Church, would, if they were now alive, do no leſs, in favour of the <hi>taking this Oath;</hi> eſpecially, by ſuch as are of our Brethrens Principles, and ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuppoſed to take it in the <hi>more rigorous,</hi> when the <hi>words will fairly bear a milder and more moderate Senſe;</hi> which the ſaid Dr. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi> allows to the <hi>takers of the Engagement,</hi> even though the <hi>Impoſers intended</hi> it, (ſo long as they declared not that they did ſo) in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a more <hi>disputable nature,</hi> and <hi>higher Obligation.</hi> And now, having diſpatched this <hi>Propoſition</hi> alſo, I proceed to the Tenth and laſt, which is,</p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>[That the Primitive Chriſtians, not only in our Saviours, and his Apoſtles days, (as had been made evident by many learned Pens;) but alſo, for ſeveral Ages after them, have governed themſelves, in point of actual Allegiance, by theſe Meaſures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did ſo; even when the Titles both of the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Governors <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <hi>his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Letter.</hi>
               </note> were either notoriouſly Faulty, or (at beſt) ſuſpicious enough; is abundantly proved by the learned Pen of a <hi>reverend Biſhop</hi> of this Church lately. And for the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Ages,</hi> if what <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſays of them be true, <hi>[That through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Empire, the Chriſtians were ſo numerous, that they filled the Cities, Iſles, Caſtles, Camp, Senate,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to that Degree, that (as he tells the Perſecutors) the very Seceſſion or Departure of ſo many Perſons from the Societies to which they belonged, into any place out of the Roman Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories (though they did nothing elſe to their prejudice) would have made a vaſt Solitude, ſuch as would have endangered the Roman Empire.]</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing (I ſay) this to be true; it is a great <hi>Evidence</hi> to me, that in all the <hi>Conteſts</hi> which then fell out (ſometimes every other, or, at leaſt, every third or fourth year, betwixt ſeveral <hi>Pretenders</hi> to the <hi>Imperial Throne,</hi> ſo that divers times the ſeveral Armies in ſeveral Provinces, ſet up Two or Three at once) the Chriſtians, who inhabited thoſe Provinces, did take the <hi>Military Oath,</hi> and pay their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> each of them to that <hi>Perſon</hi> who was inveſted with the <hi>Imperial Robes</hi> in the Parts where they ſeverally lived, when once he aſſumed that Dignity; and did not trouble themſelves to enquire whether any
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56717:15"/> that was ſet up in any other Province, had a <hi>better Title,</hi> than their <hi>own Emperour</hi> had. Which is that (as I conceive) which <hi>Tertullian</hi> elſewhere means, when he tells <hi>Scapula</hi> (the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour)</hi> who then lived in <hi>Africa, that none of the Chriſtians were ever convicted to have been Albinians, or Nigrians, or Caſſians;</hi> in all thoſe <hi>Turns</hi> which fell out under thoſe <hi>Competitors</hi> for the Crown, from whom their Partiſans were ſo named. He means not, certainly, that none of them were in the <hi>Gariſons</hi> or <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>Claudius Albinus,</hi> or <hi>Peſcennius Niger,</hi> who ſtrugled with the Emperour <hi>Severus;</hi> or of <hi>Avidius Caſſius,</hi> who conteſted with the Emperour <hi>Verus;</hi> (for this had been contrary to what he aſſerted elſewhere, that they filled <hi>their Garriſons and Armies,</hi> as before;) but only, that they were none of the <hi>Contrivers</hi> or <hi>Plotters</hi> of thoſe Wars which were by thoſe Competitors ſet on foot; nor active <hi>Sticklers</hi> for the Parties then made; for thoſe (ſays he) that were upon that account called <hi>Albinians</hi> and <hi>Nigrians, &amp;c.</hi> were the Men of their own <hi>Heatheniſh Religion,</hi> that <hi>Swore by the Genius of their Emperours,</hi> which Chriſtians refuſed to do. And when any of the ſeveral <hi>Competitors conquered,</hi> (though poſſibly, his <hi>Right</hi> were more diſputable then that of the <hi>Pretender</hi> who was <hi>overcome;</hi> yet) they adhered even to <hi>him,</hi> when once <hi>ſetled</hi> upon the <hi>Throne.</hi> And for this, I think, I have evident proof, from the view of the Emperours, whoſe Cauſe <hi>Tertullian</hi> owns in that <hi>Defence</hi> of his but now quoted: eſpecially one of them, <hi>(Severus)</hi> who raiſed the <hi>Sixth Perſecution</hi> againſt the Chriſtians. It is evident that <hi>Tertullian</hi> commends the carriage of the Chriſtians in their Obedience to <hi>Severus,</hi> becauſe he mentions <hi>Peſcennius Niger,</hi> and <hi>Claudius Albinus,</hi> as the <hi>Heads</hi> of thoſe <hi>Factions,</hi> which for oppoſing him were then odious to <hi>Severus;</hi> and denies the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to have been their <hi>Partiſans againſt him.</hi> Whence it is plain, that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſced in <hi>Severus</hi> his Title; although it be evident, that his <hi>Title,</hi> (till <hi>Conqueſt</hi> confirmed it) was the worſt of two of his <hi>Competitors.</hi> For <hi>Herodian</hi> tells us, that immediately upon the Death of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinax, Julian</hi> Firſt, and then, <hi>Peſcennius Niger,</hi> were choſen <hi>Emperors,</hi> and ſet in the Throne by their <hi>Souldiers,</hi> before <hi>Severus</hi> his Title was ſet on foot by his <hi>Troops.</hi> So that <hi>Severus</hi> himſelf was, while the Conteſt laſted, more truly a Rebel againſt <hi>Niger,</hi> then <hi>Niger</hi> againſt him. But whilſt <hi>Niger</hi> delays and revels at <hi>Antioch, Severus</hi> coming to, and maſtering <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Senate</hi> confirmed him Emperour, and then all the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> acquieſced in him, and became peaceably his good and loyal <hi>Subjects.</hi> Whence it appears plain, that the <hi>Principle</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> then was, <hi>That they were obliged to be Subjects</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:56717:15"/> 
               <hi>to whatever Prince God by his Providence had actually at any time placed on the Throne, though his Title were none of the beſt:</hi> At leaſt, they made it not a <hi>Concern</hi> of theirs, whether it were ſo <hi>good</hi> as it ſhould be.</p>
            <p>And indeed, (to draw to an end of this Diſcourſe) what ſhould a Chriſtian do, in dubious Circumſtances, but determine his <hi>Actual Allegiance,</hi> by the <hi>Iſſues</hi> of <hi>Divine Providence?</hi> For, does the <hi>great Governour</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> take it for his <hi>ſole Prerogative,</hi> to <hi>rule in the Kingdom of Men, and give it to whomſoever he will? to change times and Seaſons, to remove Kings and ſet up Kings</hi> (in the places of thoſe he removes) as in <hi>Daniel</hi> he affirms; and ſhall we Worms, <hi>ſay to him, what doſt thou?</hi> Or, is it requiſite, that he ſhould be obliged to comply with our <hi>various Opinions,</hi> in making ſuch Changes? or to tye himſelf to ſuch limited <hi>Methods</hi> in the ways of bringing them about, as beſt ſuit our <hi>Models</hi> or ſuppoſed <hi>legal Conſtitutions?</hi> Where were then this his <hi>Super-Sovereign Prerogative,</hi> if ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for its <hi>Regulation</hi> to this or that <hi>Party</hi> of Chriſtians, and not to be put in Execution, but where and when they pleaſe?</p>
            <p>But, <hi>you will</hi> ſay, <hi>Is Chriſtianity then ſo flexible a Religion, as to be able to accommodate it ſelf to all Turns and Changes?</hi> This looks like a <hi>ſafe Principle,</hi> taken up rather from the Writings and Practices of ſome <hi>worldly Politicians,</hi> then from the <hi>inflexible Rules</hi> of <hi>Divine Verity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were, indeed, ſo, if <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> had given us any ſuch <hi>inflexible Rule</hi> in ſuch Matters: or (ſeeing it hath not, as before you are told) taught us to change <hi>Deſigns,</hi> and <hi>Intereſts,</hi> and <hi>Parties,</hi> as oft as we ſee God by his Providence making way for the <hi>change</hi> of <hi>Perſons;</hi> and in order thereto, as <hi>Politicians</hi> do, to forecaſt by Humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, which is likely to be the <hi>ſtrongeſt ſide,</hi> and then (without reſpect to <hi>Honour, Honeſty,</hi> or <hi>Conſcience)</hi> to accommodate our <hi>Sails</hi> before-hand to every <hi>Wind</hi> which our <hi>Political Almanack</hi> tells us is likely to <hi>blow;</hi> that we may, by our <hi>forward appearing,</hi> merit the more from thoſe whom we oblige by our aſſiſtance in their Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That <hi>Compliance,</hi> therefore, which I plead for, as <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> is not of that Nature: It ſuffers <hi>Gods Providence,</hi> firſt, to <hi>determine,</hi> and then <hi>follows</hi> it: it is not <hi>forward</hi> in making, or aſſiſting Changes, but only <hi>ſubmits</hi> to them, or rather to <hi>God in them,</hi> when <hi>made</hi> to its hand. Nor is it haſty to ſtrike in with the <hi>firſt</hi> (like thoſe that ſtrove to get in before others to the <hi>Pool</hi> of <hi>Betheſda)</hi> when thoſe changes are made, as if it feared to loſe the Opportunity of a Market for its advantage: but allows it ſelf convenient time for due <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56717:16"/> wherein, and to what Degree, the preſent Circumſtances may be complied with, in conſiſtence with the juſt Meaſures of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> the Rules of <hi>Decency,</hi> and the Security of a good <hi>Conſcience</hi> towards God and towards Man. And then (ſo far as it may, with ſafety to all theſe, and not a jot farther) <hi>accommodates</hi> it ſelf to the preſent State of Affairs; quietly acquieſcing in the <hi>Events</hi> wherein God declares his <hi>Providential Will,</hi> though never ſo much againſt the Grain of a Man's own Inclinations or Intereſts. There is, indeed, a ſuperior Degree of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> due to the <hi>Almighty,</hi> beyond all that can be challenged by any <hi>Mortal</hi> from us; and we muſt <hi>ſit down under the ſhadow</hi> which he hath ſpread over us for our Protection; with great care, that no <hi>Diſcontent</hi> at perſonal Loſſes or Diſappointments, or any other <hi>unquiet Paſſion,</hi> hurry us into any Deſigns or Actions, which may involve us in the Guilt of <hi>fighting againſt God,</hi> by ſtriving to <hi>build up</hi> again, what he hath <hi>pulled down,</hi> or to <hi>pull down</hi> what he hath <hi>built.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, in this caſe, when God providentially rejects a <hi>Saul;</hi> though <hi>perſonal Affection,</hi> and the <hi>Hand</hi> he himſelf formerly had, under God, in <hi>raiſing</hi> him to the <hi>Throne,</hi> and ſupporting him in it, may excuſe an Holy <hi>Samuel,</hi> in the <hi>condoling Reſentment</hi> he ſhewed at the Change, and the <hi>compaſſionate Mourning</hi> which he inwardly put on for the <hi>unhappy Prince:</hi> Yet, even <hi>He,</hi> muſt thenceforth look upon himſelf, as diſcharged from any farther (at leaſt publick) <hi>owning</hi> his <hi>Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> towards him. And it is evident, he did ſo. For, otherwiſe, ſo great a <hi>Courtier</hi> as <hi>Samuel</hi> had been, through all <hi>Saul</hi>'s former Reign, could hardly have diſpenſed with himſelf for the ſeeming Incivility of not ſo much as giving him <hi>one Viſit</hi> from the Time when he received the notice of his Rejection from God, and (by his command) delivered the unwelcome Tidings thereof to him, <hi>till the day of his death.</hi> And even that <hi>Humane Reſentment,</hi> which for a ſeaſon is excuſable in ſuch a caſe, yet muſt be managed with great <hi>Moderation,</hi> and not lodge too <hi>long</hi> in his Boſom. For God himſelf takes him off from it at laſt, when he ſaw it exceſſive, with a Repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>How long</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>wilt thou mourn for Saul, ſeeing I have rejected him?</hi> Now, if the bare <hi>antecedent notice</hi> from God to his <hi>Prophet,</hi> that he had ſententially rejected <hi>Saul</hi> from the Kingdom whilſt yet he continued in the <hi>Land,</hi> and actually exerciſed his <hi>Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> ſtill, and for ſome years after) might lawfully ſo far leſſen the Obligation of <hi>Samuel</hi>'s <hi>Allegiance,</hi> as to warrant his abſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo long from Court, (which very withdrawing of his, could not, in ſo eminent and conſpicuous a Perſon as he was, but argue a great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56717:16"/> Diſlike, and therefore, in the Judgment of the common People, have a very ill Aſpect upon the <hi>Kings Affairs;)</hi> it is not difficult to imagine how much farther he might have concluded himſelf diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from it, in caſe <hi>Saul</hi> had, upon his Denunciation of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection from God, and the change in the Countenances, and ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious carriage of the chief of the People (plainly intimated, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 30.) actually <hi>withdrawn</hi> himſelf out of his Kingdom; and from his native Subjects of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> retired to Nations in <hi>Enmity</hi> with them; (eſpecially, if he had applied himſelf to the <hi>Egyptians</hi> their old Maſters, and to the <hi>Philistines,</hi> their moſt ſpightful <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers,</hi> and therefore the <hi>moſt dreaded Adverſaries</hi> they had,) and moreover ſollicited their <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> to reſtore and reſettle him in his Dominions by <hi>Conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, that ſome Learned Men (and among the reſt, <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> particularly,) in this Caſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> conjecture that <hi>Samuel,</hi> went ſomewhat farther yet, in ſhewing his <hi>Duty</hi> to the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected King,</hi> during this his retirement from Court, by his continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>pray for him</hi> ſtill. This is begged, I muſt needs ſay (with the leave of thoſe learned Authors,) for it cannot be proved. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if granted, we muſt ſuppoſe it only done where he <hi>mourned for him,</hi> that is, in <hi>private.</hi> And for the <hi>matter</hi> of his <hi>Prayers;</hi> it could not be, <hi>That God would reſtore him abſolutely,</hi> but only, <hi>conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</hi> upon his <hi>Repentance:</hi> and ſo, as no <hi>conſiderable damage</hi> might accrew to <hi>Gods Church</hi> and People thereby. And, in ſuch <hi>ſecret De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions,</hi> and ſo <hi>cautioned,</hi> there is none, who will (I ſuppoſe) forbid any one, even now, to exerciſe the <hi>Remains</hi> of his <hi>former Loyalty,</hi> who thinks himſelf obliged ſo to do.</p>
            <p>And, as far, to the utmoſt, as <hi>Samuels Loyalty</hi> is ſuppoſed by any one to have gone in <hi>Sauls Caſe:</hi> I doubt not, but <hi>divers</hi> (at leaſt) of the <hi>Reverend Perſons</hi> this Paper was in a great meaſure meant for, have followed his <hi>Example,</hi> in this preſent Juncture. They have, as long as K. <hi>J.</hi> was <hi>on the Throne,</hi> and exerciſed his <hi>Regality,</hi> born with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers harſh and uneaſie encroachments of <hi>Prerogative-Power;</hi> and ſome in an eminent and exemplary degree, practiſed the <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> they taught, to the no ſmall credit of our Church and its Loyal Principles; (and I am aſſured, upon my own knowledge, that not a few of their Brethren, both of the <hi>Epiſcopal Character,</hi> and of the <hi>Inferiour Clergy,</hi> (who in the preſent Caſe, differ from them) were ready, if like <hi>occaſion</hi> had been offered, to have followed them in the <hi>ſame ſteps,</hi> wherein they led them by ſo good an Example: they have alſo (as moſt of the ſacred Function have likewiſe done) kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56717:17"/> within the bounds of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> that is, free from contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting towards the <hi>effecting</hi> of that <hi>great change</hi> which God by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual methods of aſtoniſhing Providence hath made: they have, (thoſe of them, at leaſt, whoſe high Stations gave them a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Influence upon publick Affairs,) conſcientiouſly endeavoured, by their Counſels to hinder things from arriving to that <hi>Extremity</hi> to which they are now reduced: and ſince, (for 'tis no news, nor, I think, will they themſelves think it a diſparagement or diſſervice to them to have it here publiſhed) they have <hi>ſat down</hi> under them, not only, with a <hi>Samuel-like condolency</hi> with the <hi>diſpoſſeſſed King,</hi> but alſo, with ſome <hi>uneaſineſs</hi> to their own circumſtances, under ſome <hi>publick Acts</hi> wherein they are diſſatisfied: they have alſo <hi>ſhewn</hi> their <hi>diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions,</hi> by their <hi>ſlowneſs</hi> to comply with the preſent Eſtabliſhment; even to the ſuffering a <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> from the Execution of their Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical employments: and it may be, they do ſecretly <hi>pray</hi> for (what they wiſh, if it might be) the <hi>retrieving</hi> of things into a <hi>ſtate</hi> more <hi>ſuitable to their own Principles;</hi> whiles God, by his Providence ſeems ſtill to ſay <hi>nay,</hi> to all ſuch Deſires, and attempts; except we will be content to purchaſe them (as matters now ſtand) upon ſuch Terms, as (in all humane Reaſon) muſt be deſtructive to all that is <hi>dear</hi> to us and them too, both in our <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore, ſeeing (as I have already ſhewn) there can be no more <hi>lawfully done</hi> for him, whom Gods Providence hath thus <hi>exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> I cannot imagine, what ſhould farther influence our <hi>Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and worthily eſteemed <hi>Brethren,</hi> to adventure the expoſing themſelves to the <hi>extremities</hi> of the <hi>Law:</hi> and not rather exerciſe their <hi>Paſſive Principles</hi> (at leaſt) under the <hi>preſent Authority</hi> (for ſurely, there is a kind of <hi>Paſſivity</hi> in it, when one <hi>ſubmits</hi> to what he is not <hi>pleaſed</hi> with) which the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> and the moſt <hi>Eminent Divines</hi> of our Church too, in the days of K. <hi>Ch.</hi> I. and K. <hi>Ch.</hi> II. (by our preceding meaſures taken of them,) would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not have ſtuck at, in our caſe; by transferring that <hi>Actual Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> which they cannot pay <hi>elſewhere,</hi> to thoſe to whom Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath transferred the <hi>Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not here (as I told you at the beginning) to add farther ſtrength to my Cauſe, urge the Arguments which many other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have chiefly inſiſted upon, (to reconcile our Brethrens Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereto) from the <hi>rationality</hi> and <hi>legality</hi> of the Circumſtances relating to the production of this great change. And yet I find my ſelf ſtrongly inclined (in the cloſe of this Diſcourſe) to offer <hi>one</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:56717:17"/> (to debate at leaſt) from one of the often-mentioned Dr. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſons</hi> Principles: which if it prove ſound, (and I have not yet met with any one that hath attempted to overthrow it,) will, (for ought I can yet ſee to the contrary) do much, toward the clearing them in <hi>both reſpects.</hi> It is (in a word) this, Among the <hi>other Caſes,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Reverend Doctor</hi> tells us, the <hi>obligation</hi> of a <hi>Promiſſory Oath ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> he makes this <hi>one. [When the ſtate of things is ſo altered betwixt the Time of a Mans taking ſuch an Oath,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sanderſon</hi> De Juramenti obligatione.</note> 
               <hi>and that, wherein the performance is expected; that if ſuch a change could have been foreſeen by the ſwearer, he would have forborn to take it:]</hi> to which I would add, <hi>[or would, at leaſt, (if he could have apprehended it but poſſible, and much more, if likely to fall out, beforehand) have made the falling out of what he ſo apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, an expreſs exception to the obligation thereof.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt ingenuouſly confeſs, (with all due deference to the Judgment of ſo <hi>profound</hi> a <hi>Caſuiſt)</hi> I think my ſelf not neceſſarily <hi>obliged</hi> to <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert</hi> the <hi>verity</hi> of this <hi>Hypotheſis, univerſally,</hi> in all Caſes that might be put of this nature. And yet, I am apt to think, the <hi>ſpecial Inſtance</hi> which he there gives, hath more in it, then will eaſily be diſproved, in any <hi>Caſe parallel</hi> to it. The <hi>Caſe</hi> he puts is this. <hi>[A Father ſwears to his Son, that having by his avowed Will and Teſtament, bequeathed all his Eſtate when he dyes, to him: he will never revoke that Deed. But in ſome Time after, he finds by undoubted Evidence that this Son of his hath attempted by Poyſon to deſtroy him.]</hi> In this Caſe, (ſays the <hi>Reverend Doctor) He may, (notwithſtanding his former Oath to the contrary,) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcind that Will, and by a conſequent one, is at liberty to make a new and different diſpoſal of that Eſtate.]</hi> The <hi>Reaſon</hi> of which <hi>Determination,</hi> ſuits his preceeding <hi>Theſis:</hi> to wit, becauſe the <hi>caſe is now ſo altered to the Father, that if he could have foreſeen it, he would never have taken that Oath.</hi> For the <hi>Father</hi> ſwore it to a <hi>Son,</hi> a <hi>Son,</hi> then ſuppoſed to be <hi>dutiful,</hi> and one from whom he expected the <hi>continuance</hi> of his <hi>filial Duty</hi> (eſpecially he knowing himſelf to be ſo highly obliged to continue ſo by ſo late a Demonſtration of his Fatherly kindneſs,) <hi>until the day of his natural Death.</hi> And little could he imagine, (much leſs foreknow, that his <hi>Son</hi> would ſo far deceive his expectation, as to become in ſtead of a <hi>Son,</hi> an <hi>Enemy;</hi> in ſtead of a <hi>dutiful Son,</hi> a <hi>mortal Enemy</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Father:</hi> in ſtead of one that would <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently expect</hi> his <hi>natural Death,</hi> had endeavoured to <hi>haſten</hi> it, by <hi>Violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if the <hi>Doctors</hi> reſolution in this Caſe, be good, and ſolid: it ſeems to be, no leſs, in the <hi>Reverſe</hi> of it; that is, ſuppoſing the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56717:18"/> 
               <hi>Son</hi> by a like <hi>Oath</hi> alſo obliged to the <hi>Father.</hi> Lay we the Caſe thus, with the due variation of circumſtances. <hi>[The Son mentioned, upon his Fathers Oath ſo paſſed, not only to maintain him as his Son, whiles he lives; but alſo to leave him at his death, a fair Eſtate derived to him from his Anceſtors, and entailed to him as his next Heir: and whatſoever of his own he hath by his induſtrious improvements added to it likewiſe: doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally engage (by Oath alſo) to his Father, to remain under his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and in his Family, and aſſiſt him in the preſervation and utmoſt improvement of that Eſtate, while he lives: and in a word, to be deficient in no Duty, incumbent on him by vertue of that ne'ar relation, and obliging kindneſs. But the Father, after theſe mutual Engagements thus paſſed, (not provoked by any undutiful Demeanour of his Son, but out of an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular affection unto ſome ſtranger, who hath inſinuated himſelf into his favour by ſordid ſlattery and falſe ſuggeſtions,) doth not only carry himſelf towards his Son, in a ſtrange unfatherly and unnatural way of rigour, and uſeth him more like a ſlave, then a child; but alſo, (even openly, and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facedly) attempts to diſinherit him at his death, by cutting off the legal entail of thoſe antient Lands from him; and (to make the injury more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſs) endeavours in his own life time, to poſſeſs that Perſon whom he hath entertained this new kindneſs for, of the whole Eſtate, by ſurrender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his Deeds and Evidences relating to it, together with his own Perſon alſo, into his hands and abſolute Power. So that now, the Son can no longer either perform the matter of his Oath to him, or, indeed, come at him, in the circumſtances wherein he is, without inevitable danger of his own life, from the malicious attempts of his competitor, (too much encouraged in them alſo by his Father) whoſe Intereſt it is to deſtroy him, as the only Perſon from whom he expects, at the Fathers death, to be diſturbed in his ill-gotten and unjuſt Poſſeſſions.]</hi> Now here, I would fain know, why (upon the <hi>Doctors</hi> Grounds) the <hi>Son,</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>obligation</hi> of <hi>natural Duty,</hi> though confirmed alſo by an <hi>Oath,</hi> may not think himſelf at liberty, (under ſuch unexpected and ſurpriſing diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from his <hi>Fathers</hi> alteration towards him to ſuch an high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of unnatural and unjuſt dealing, which he no way foreſaw, nor could foreſee, when he made that Oath to him) and why he may not accept of the tendred <hi>Protection</hi> and <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of ſome other <hi>near Relation,</hi> (or <hi>any one,</hi> indeed, who hath ſo great a kindneſs as to afford it him, and is able probably, to ſupport him againſt ſuch an outragious Injury) both (as to the ſafety of his <hi>Perſon,)</hi> by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving into his <hi>Family,</hi> and alſo, (as to the <hi>Eſtate,)</hi> by ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſo far as lawfully he may, by all the aſſiſtance he can give, for the ſecuring, (at leaſt) of that <hi>Inheritance,</hi> (which is rightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56717:18"/> 
               <hi>his</hi> in the <hi>Reverſion,</hi> and cannot legally be alienated from him,) even while his <hi>unnatural Father</hi> is yet <hi>living.</hi> Yea, why he may not, if demanded, (for the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of him, who adventures ſo far on his behalf, to create himſelf ſo great <hi>Enmities)</hi> alſo, give his generous <hi>Protector</hi> and <hi>Guardian</hi> the <hi>utmoſt aſſurance</hi> that he can require, (even that of an <hi>Oath,</hi> like that which he gave his <hi>Father</hi> himſelf,) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the performance of all that <hi>Duty,</hi> (whiles he thus continues under his <hi>Roof,</hi> and enjoyes the benefit of his <hi>Guardianſhip,</hi> which had continued due to his <hi>Father,</hi> if he had continued a <hi>Father</hi> to him, to his <hi>dying day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Caſe, if I am not much miſtaken, ſeems thus far, very fair on the <hi>Sons</hi> ſide: eſpecially, if (in the mean while of the <hi>neceſſary ceſſation of his actual Duty to his Father,)</hi> he perform no <hi>poſitive Act</hi> of <hi>undutifulneſs</hi> to him who hath ſo <hi>diſobliged</hi> him, by way of <hi>retalia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> and be <hi>diſpoſitively ready</hi> to return to all that duty again, which he formerly paid him, in caſe he <hi>change his mind</hi> towards him, <hi>reſtore</hi> him to his former Circumſtances, and give him that <hi>rational ſecurity</hi> that in ſuch a caſe is requiſite; to aſſure him againſt any <hi>future re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laps</hi> into the like unnatural deſigns and attempts againſt him.</p>
            <p>Let now, <hi>this Caſe</hi> be ſeriouſly conſidered by thoſe who are moſt diſſatisfied, (provided, they be not over-byaſſed by contrary Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts,) as it makes too <hi>unhappy a Parallel</hi> to our <hi>late</hi> and <hi>preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances:</hi> and I am in great hope, that they will (at leaſt) ſee cauſe to <hi>judge tenderly</hi> concerning ſome <hi>ambiguous actions</hi> of thoſe, who have by <hi>extraordinary methods</hi> (even againſt their Inclinations) hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſacred to <hi>them</hi> (yea to all of <hi>us,</hi> and our <hi>Poſterity after us</hi> too) thoſe <hi>dear Enjoyments and Reverſions,</hi> which were lately even upon the <hi>Point</hi> of being <hi>loſt</hi> for <hi>ever:</hi> if not alſo, farther, to <hi>thank</hi> that <hi>great Deliverer,</hi> whom God hath gratiouſly by extraordinary Providence, ſent them and us: and <hi>laſt</hi> of all, to <hi>give</hi> him all that <hi>legal ſecurity,</hi> which he hath reaſon to expect; that whiles they ſit ſafe under his <hi>ſhadow,</hi> they will not undermine the <hi>Tree</hi> from which it comes; but demean themſelves with that <hi>fidelity to him</hi> which ſo great a <hi>favour</hi> deſerves.</p>
            <p>The obtaining of which <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>reaſonable things</hi> (as till I am otherwiſe convinced I muſt judge them to be,) at the hands of our yet <hi>unſatisfied Brethren,</hi> is that which I have all along endeavoured in this <hi>diſcourſe;</hi> which now I think it time to <hi>end,</hi> being afraid, that I have too long exerciſed my <hi>Readers Patience</hi> with its <hi>prolixity.</hi> But I muſt not diſmiſs it, without ſending this ſhort <hi>Prayer</hi> along with it. That God will vouchſafe to <hi>ſpeed</hi> it with a <hi>ſucceſs</hi> anſwerable to the <hi>ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56717:19"/> of my <hi>Intentions</hi> therein; for the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of all thoſe for whom it was deſigned, (whether exceptious <hi>Friends,</hi> or ſerupulous <hi>Brethren,</hi> or prejudicated <hi>Enemies</hi> to the Cauſe I plead:) and make us all, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cordially <hi>unanimous</hi> in it; or (whiles we cannot be ſo) more <hi>charitable</hi> each to other, in our <hi>differences</hi> of <hi>Opinion,</hi> then (according to the <hi>unhappy Fate</hi> which amongſt us in <hi>England,</hi> too commonly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends all <hi>Controverſies)</hi> we are wont to be: That our <hi>common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> may not have the pleaſure of ſeeing us do that by our own <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent, unſeaſonable,</hi> and <hi>unchriſtian Diviſions,</hi> which, without them, all the <hi>Intrigues</hi> of <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf, in conjunction with the <hi>Deſigns</hi> and <hi>Arms</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and its <hi>Adherents,</hi> (I hope in God) ſhall never he able to do.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Amen,</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56717:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
